For over a century, the legendary tales
that have surrounded our great British
airfields have inspired generations of
people, [music] including me. Which is
why I am on a personal mission to cross
the UK to visit some of our most
important airfields to understand not
just about their contribution [music] to
our past, but importantly how many of
them have helped define our future. From
the UK's first flight through to
groundbreaking innovation such as carbon
fiber and the jet engine, the
extraordinary effort spent on preserving
our aviation heritage. Join me as I
explore the story of the airfields that
have helped shape Britain and the world.
This is Stow Maries in Essex and it is
the most complete surviving example of a
First World War aerodrome anywhere in
Britain. Many of its original structures
survive, a good number of which are
being lovingly restored to give us a
fascinating insight into the UK's first
pilots during those heady days of early
military aviation.
Stow Maries life as an active aerodrome
was incredibly brief. It lasted only
three years between 1916 and 1919. But
the pilots based here really were the
pioneers of aerial combat. And when you
think about it, they were tasked with
taking a technology barely 10 years old
to war.
At the outbreak of the First World War
in 1914,
Britain really had only about 90
military aircraft and they
>> [music]
>> were used for reconnaissance. The
airfields they used were pretty simple
affairs, just like this one. Grass
strips with a scattering of buildings
and tents upon them.
As far as the British government were
concerned, the idea of using aircraft as
weapons [music]
hadn't really occurred to them.
Hello, Trevor.
How do you do? Good to see you, mate.
>> Yeah, you too. You too.
Trevor, when we look back over a century
to the beginning of the First World War,
it's hard to imagine a time when
aircraft didn't have a combat role, but
in 1914,
that wasn't the case. You've got to look
back and and sort of remember that the
years 100 years ago, they were working
with the technology that they had at the
time. Um most of the aircraft which were
available,
um not just to the military,
um were very very rudimentary. Um
powered flight had only been achieved uh
around 10 years beforehand when the
Wright brothers first took to the air.
And many of the aircraft were were
literally kites with engines.
Um and they weren't really built for
that sort of uh sort of role. Here at
Stow Maries, we've got a fantastic
example of a First World War era drone.
But the infrastructure that the RFC had
to rely upon was pretty basic, wasn't
it?
It was. Um
obviously deploying aircraft to a combat
area
um is one thing, but you know, England
itself, the UK mainland, was not really,
I don't think, perceived as being under
threat from the air. Um
and really the airfields in England were
perhaps geared towards training. They
were geared towards um the logistics of
moving aircraft around, delivering them
to squadrons, sort of aircraft parks
such as Farnborough.
Um so, I know you we are very much in
the days before people thinking about
home defense and building airfields in
the UK to destroy or prevent incoming
bomber raids.
However, German forces realized early
the destructive potential of aerial
warfare, employing not only airplanes,
but also airships, most famously
zeppelins. The Germans began bombing
British cities in January 1915 with
these titans of the sky. During the
First World War, there was a significant
amount of damage caused in air raids. Um
however, very little of that is visible
to this day. Um
much heavy bombing in World War II uh
meant that much of London has been
rebuilt in the intervening years.
However, here in Lincoln's Inn, there is
still some tangible evidence of one of
those first early air raids caused by a
Zeppelin. On the night of the 13th of
October, 1915, a Zeppelin commanded by a
Kapitänleutnant Joachim Breithaupt
[music]
appeared over London and dropped his
first bomb over Charing Cross Station. A
few minutes later, a bomb landed here in
Lincoln's Inn and landed right on the
point on the ground there, marked by
that marker.
The blast, while it didn't kill anyone,
um
sent out uh
>> [music]
>> fragments of shrapnel all over the walls
here and you can still see where that
shrapnel has gouged out holes. [music]
The blast from the bomb also smashed a
17th-century stained glass window up
above there. Although no one was killed
here, a total of 47 people were killed
in London that night.
What the Germans hoped uh to create
panic in the streets of of Britain with
their bombing campaign, in many cases it
was actually the complete opposite.
People were fascinated by this whole new
experience and many people had never
seen an airplane, certainly never seen
an airship. Then actually, spotting
Zeppelins became [music] a bit of a
spectator sport. There was something
fascinating about looking up into the
sky and seeing a silver Zeppelin
illuminated by these sweeping
searchlights with shells bursting all
around like like twinkling stars. A
Zeppelin attack had a a certain unreal
beauty all of its own.
Although the the Germans tried to create
[music] the impression that they were
doing accurate bombing, really
bomb aiming techniques at this time were
quite unsophisticated and really, once
you got over central London, [music] the
idea was to just release your bombs in a
regular pattern and hope you hit
something significant.
Zeppelins were giant hydrogen-filled
airships with the biggest during World
War I reaching 650 ft in length. They
weighed 34 tons and could [music] carry
1 and 1/2 to 3 tons of bombs.
The Zeppelins were the largest combat
aircraft ever to have flown.
The German bombing raids were not as
effective as they'd hoped, but they
still caused significant damage and
casualties, with some 500 people killed
in raids across [music] Britain.
The Dolphin pub, Red Lion Street,
Bloomsbury in Central London.
Here, on the 8th of September, 1915,
another air raid caused devastating
damage. A bomb landed at the front
entrance to this pub, blasted out a
whole glass frontage, and killed a a
local man who was standing by the door
at the time. But, a clock that was on
the wall in the pub that day was
shattered by the blast, and its hands
stopped at the time of detonation, at
10:49 in the evening. That clock is
still on the wall now. The hands have
dropped a little to uh time has had an
effect, and they now show 10:40, but it
is the original clock that stopped
working in that air raid of the 8th of
September, 1915.
These Zeppelin raids on Britain caused
an unexpected uh impact, in so much that
rather than panic setting in, um
people were incensed by these raids. The
the the German Zeppelins became known as
the baby killers. Um um what it saw in
after every single raid, there was a a
dramatic increase in the number of
people wanting to join up the army. So,
rather than working against Britain, it
actually had an effect of creating more
recruits for the army, something that
the the German commanders had never
anticipated.
Another interesting reaction to these
Zeppelin raids was the amount of um
picture postcards that were produced,
and people seem to have an insatiable
desire for them. The these postcards
showed uh dramatic images of Zeppelins
being shot down, exploding in the air.
And even in fact, uh much to a general
surprise, there was a very popular range
of comic postcards, with people joking
about these Zeppelin raids.
Although the Zeppelin attacks were
[music] not going to win the war for the
Germans, the British couldn't stand by
while the enemy dropped bombs with
impunity. I think the government
response basically was that they had to
do something. [music] There would have
been mounting public pressure to
actually respond and do something
positive to stop or at least disrupt
these [music] raids. Specifically with
regards to the Zeppelin raids, it was to
build airfields and a home defense
network including such places as Stow
Maries where we are now. So this arose
because [music] of the Zeppelin threat.
Absolutely. Yes, directly. Part of sort
of home defense wing
of the Royal Flying Corps
which was put in place to [music]
disrupt or destroy these incoming raids.
Stow Maries is on the River Blackwater.
The River Blackwater is a big river.
It's a it's a navigation [music]
aid to
aircraft in the air.
So you can follow the Blackwater right
to your target which might be London.
[music] Same with the River Thames. So
you'd have squadrons based where they
think
>> [music]
>> they're going to be most useful.
>> These days of course airships are pretty
unfamiliar to most of us.
But it's interesting to think that this
entire establishment was born [music]
out
of a fear of them. It was not only a
fear, it was a very very real threat.
But Stow Maries [music] continued to be
relevant because as that threat of the
Zeppelin
subsided, it was superseded by
multi-engine aircraft such as the Gotha,
big German bombers coming over the
country to continue the work that had
been started by the Zeppelin. So Stow
Maries was here to deal with that.
In 1916, the home defense wings were
formed and began patrolling the skies
around London. But they were just part
of a much more extensive defense system
that was rapidly being put into place.
While David Henderson, head of the Royal
Flying Corps, oversaw the construction
of airfields around London, Admiral Sir
Percy Scott started the implementation
of gun rings around the capital.
Until late 1915, London's air defense
had consisted of three outdated guns
placed on Whitehall buildings.
They did give some protection to the
seat of government, but by the middle of
World War I,
this began to change.
By 1917, Britain at last had a decent
air defense system consisting of
anti-aircraft guns, searchlights,
aircraft, and a centralized command
system. But crucially, the Royal Flying
Corps were also about to get their hands
on a vital ingredient in the fight
against the Zeppelin. Incendiary
bullets.
Dave.
Hi Jules. How are you, sir? Nice to see
you. And to you, sir. Look at that.
That's a beauty. Yep.
>> Tell us what we're looking at here.
First World War Vickers machine gun.
Standard .303 machine gun of the British
Army in the First World War.
Now, you would think that shooting down
an enormous airship with a machine gun
like that would be a fairly
straightforward operation.
You would think so, wouldn't you? But
it's it's not quite that
straightforward. The problem is is
inside a structure of a Zeppelin, you
have cells.
Sort of represented like this black bag
here.
That's basically what it is. Several of
these cells inside the the airship
structure.
>> And they're full of hydrogen. These are
full of hydrogen. They support a
skeleton frame which has got a skin over
it. And these little bullets
passing through there, it's it's so
small. They are so tiny.
Um all you're going to get is very, very
slow leaks. It's even slower than a slow
leak on your car tire. It's just too
small to make any real difference to
that cell. I mean, obviously this is a
representation of a hydrogen cell from a
Zeppelin, but this is
>> under-scaled.
>> a genuine .303
>> That's a genuine .303 round, standard
ball round. You're right. It doesn't
look like it's man enough to do the job
at all, does it?
>> No, and if you can imagine this cell
being the size of this room traveling
through there.
Wow. And that's one cell. Now, the
experiment today is going to illustrate
how hard it was to shoot down a Zeppelin
and importantly how we managed to tackle
the challenge head-on.
What's at the end of the range there? It
looks like a camping tent. Well, that's
our Zeppelin down there. But inside
we've got our hydrogen cells. And what
effect do you think these are going to
have? What do you think?
Is it going to go bang?
We'll see.
We will. And we get to fire this
well, beautiful antique
Vickers. Yeah. Yeah. Right then, let's
have a look.
Okay.
What we're going to do is you're going
to fire it and you're going to put a
10-round burst into that tent and you'll
just see what happens. In one go? In one
go. Right. Right, let's do it.
Gun is live.
Ear defenders on.
Okay. In your own time.
Go on.
Wow.
Okay, clear the gun.
>> amazing, actually. It's a weapon
of real presence, isn't it? It really
is. It thuds away there. You can see how
effective they were
in the trenches, but also in the air.
But
has it done the business at the far end
because the tent's still there. There
was no big bang. Let's have a look.
Well, it hasn't made as much of a mess
as I thought it would, to be honest.
Little
little spots there, aren't there? Soft
skin. Let's have a quick look around and
see what happened to the cells inside.
>> there's a little tear there. That is a
bit more dramatic. And hopefully in here
is our mock-up hydrogen cell.
>> Oh, there it is. Well, there you go.
That's it's it's got obviously got holes
in it.
And you can feel it coming out there.
So, that demonstrates perfectly a normal
round, a normal bullet, Yeah. really
isn't going to destroy a Zeppelin in the
way that we might
>> No, absolutely not.
>> The incendiary round is the thing that
really
turns the tide against the Zeppelin.
Why? What happens there you've got a
burning element. It's a tracer
basically.
That burn burning element is obviously
spitting bits of spark out behind it.
Now you've punctured the inner and outer
envelopes
of the Zeppelin. What's going to happen
is the gases are going to mix. You now
got an ignition source. And once you hit
that with two or three of these
rounds, you're going to get an
explosion. So, if we were to fill these,
once again, Yeah. and fire a tracer
round at this, that would be quite
dramatic.
I think you'll find it's a lot more
Shall we? Yeah, let's try it.
Okay. Okay. Gun is live. Okay. Eyes and
ears on.
Safety catch off.
Wow. Okay. No, we're fine.
It's a little bit low.
Too low? Little bit low, yeah.
There you go. That's right through the
middle. Okay. Okay, here we go then.
Huh!
Wow. That was
astonishing. The shockwave from the
explosion at the other end of the range
has come barreling up this concrete
tunnel.
So, now you know what it's like
>> [music]
>> to shoot at something that is very
explosive in gas.
>> And that was a tiny, tiny target. Yes.
Imagine hitting a full Bane Zeppelin.
Yes. When you hit hydrogen it's going to
burn very rapidly. So, you're going to
see the cells just to burning and
burning and hydrogen normally burns
invisibly. Well, Dave, that has been a
fascinating insight
>> [music]
>> and a real demonstration of just how
effective experimental history
experimental archaeology can be
in understanding the challenges [music]
of the past and how best they were
overcome.
Well done, you. No, well done, you. You
had the target.
The continuing [music] success of
Britain's defenses forced the Germans to
reconsider their bombing strategy.
By mid-1917,
the Germans had lost almost half of
their airships and began to
predominantly use Gotha bombers instead.
In 1916, there were still 126 airship
raids on the UK with only 28 raids by
airplanes. That statistic drastically
reversed in 1917 with 341 airplane raids
and only 30 by airships.
By replacing standard bullets with ones
that burned and could ignite the
flammable gas in the Zeppelin, [music]
the British were able to defeat the
world's first strategic bombing
campaign. The pilots here at Stow Maries
were taking on the Zeppelins and the
Gothas in essentially reconnaissance
[music] aircraft, but over the front
lines in France, a completely new
machine is beginning to dominate the air
war, the fighter.
Whilst re-purposed reconnaissance
aircraft based here at Stow Maries may
have been sufficient in attacking large
slow-moving targets such as Zeppelins
and Gotha bombers, a whole new type of
aircraft was needed to counter the
enemy's growing aviation developments.
At the start of World War I, the RFC
deployed various airplanes including
BE2s and Avro 504s.
These airplanes were only seen as useful
for observation and reconnaissance.
With a crudely attached machine gun or
armed with explosive darts, these
aircraft were later be used against
Zeppelins.
But when it came to evading and
attacking other airplanes, these stable
slow aircraft had no chance. The
airplane here, the Avro 504, was
probably one of the best training
aircraft that we developed during the
First War. It was also ideal as a
reconnaissance airplane. You could have
a pilot and an observer in the airplane.
That observer would be either taking
notes or he would taking taking
photographs or in some cases was using
simple radio to relay information to the
ground. Their task was to observe the
enemy, scouting artillery locations,
trench positions, and troop movements.
Toward the beginning of the war, these
aircraft could go about their business
relatively unopposed. [music]
So, most early reconnaissance airplanes
were unarmed.
It may be that the observer carried a
revolver, but generally speaking, the
idea was to go and observe the enemy
without having to concern yourself with
defending your own airplane. The
effectiveness [music] of these
reconnaissance flights meant that some
pilots began to feel that it might be
wise to try and down the enemy aircraft.
The guns were initially issued to the
officers for self-defense if they went
down.
Only after they started, the Germans
started it apparently taking pot shots
at the British trying to take
photographs. The British actually
complained to the German High Command
and said, "This is not on. We're trying
to take photographs. We're all officers,
and your guys are meant to be Prussian
officer corps shooting at us. How rude."
The German response was just to shoot
back. Well, I mean, it's war at the end
of the day.
Once the British understood that, that's
when the the arms race really started
then. In this drawer, we have
probably the first weapon
used in aerial combat, although it
wasn't designed as a weapon,
is a flare pistol.
But at some point, some bright spark
thought, "Ooh,
fires a distress flare, incendiary,
planes are made of wood and canvas.
I wonder what happens if I fire it at a
plane. Bang.
So, that was probably the first weapon
ever to be used in aerial combat. Uh it
didn't work, but you you know, that's
what started it all really. The standard
British pistol at the time
uh or the most common
was a Webley revolver. It's reliable.
There's nothing to go wrong. For a pilot
who's controlling an aircraft, point
and shoot.
It's a heavy bullet. It will go through
canvas. It will go through wood, which
the planes were made of. There's not a
single recorded instance of a plane or a
pilot being downed or injured or
anything with a handheld weapon. You're
in a plane. It's vibrating. It's
juddering. There's 200 mile an hour
winds rushing past you. You're freezing.
You're choking on the fumes.
Someone's trying to kill you.
Just doesn't happen.
Uh when they worked out that the pistols
really
weren't weren't cutting the mustard,
they moved over then to well, let's take
up the rifles. They're powerful rifles.
So, we have something like
the British standard short magazine
Lee-Enfield. It's an excellent weapon.
It's a
a 10-round magazine. A bullet that has a
range of a mile uh in the ideal
conditions.
It'll go through uh a brick wall. It'll
go through a tree. But, you put the
magazine in. You load the weapon.
Bang.
How are you going to fly the plane?
Again, not a single recorded instance of
it being an effective effective weapon
uh with regards to aerial combat. As an
infantry weapon, fantastic.
The enemy very rapidly um realized that
they could um
protect their forces by denying that uh
reconnaissance. The Germans developed
airplanes with the specific purpose of
shooting down reconnaissance airplanes.
We realized very rapidly that this was
beginning to happen. Designers back in
the UK knew what they had to do. They
had to produce more maneuverable
airplanes and airplanes that were more
sensible in terms of
operating machine guns. Pistols don't
work. The rifles don't work. What do we
use? The machine gun. It's the obvious
choice. Rapid rate of fire, fires a
rifle bullet, high destructive power.
The British
opted for the Lewis gun. Great gun. 47
round magazine. Fires the powerful 303
cartridge.
But you've got a propeller and you don't
want to hit a propeller cuz if you do,
the plane falls out of the air. No
point. So what the British did was they
mounted the Lewis gun up high above the
pilot. They tried putting it on the
wings which bent the wing.
What was really needed was a gun mounted
in front of the pilot which could fire
without hitting the propeller.
In July 1915, the Germans were the first
to achieve it using an interrupter or
synchronization gear on their Fokker
Eindecker.
The propeller and the machine gun was
synchronized in order to ensure the
machine gun would only fire when the
propeller blade was not passing in front
of the gun's barrel.
It gave the Germans a huge advantage and
it took the allies over a year to catch
up and develop their own system.
So the British then moved over to the
Vickers heavy machine gun fires from a
closed bolt mechanism
which means it's much more
easy to develop an interrupter system
for a plane. By the autumn of 1916,
Britain had finally developed its own
interrupter gear enabling them to mount
a Vickers gun right in front of the
pilot. So once the British finally had
the
hydraulic interrupter mechanism sorted,
they had the Vickers heavy machine gun,
the air cooled version,
a fantastic weapon. Pilots who last had
a system they could trust and use and
come off of the Lewis and the the the
Foster mount and have a weapon which was
mounted in front
uh which they could get behind,
instinctively fly the plane, get behind
the weapon, fire, engage the enemy. This
breakthrough, along with all the
experience gained from the early part of
the war, enabled British engineers to
begin producing purebred fighters,
culminating with the S.E.5a.
It was really the epitome [music]
of fighting airplanes. It was well
armed. It was easy to fly and very fast.
The airplane has a much shorter wing
uh than the the training airplanes.
Aerodynamically, it's cleaner. Now
you've got something that's going to go
fast. The guns pointed in the same
direction as the airplane. So, you could
literally use the flying machine as a
flying gun. So, by the end of the war,
aircraft had developed for specific
roles. We had bombers and we had
fighters and we had trainers. In 4 years
of the First World War, we've gone from
big, simple airplanes through to small,
powerful fighters with good controls
that really were the the way forward.
Now the invention of the interrupter
gear gave rise to the iconic dogfight
which tested both [music] pilots and
machines to their very limits.
It also, of course, meant that pilots
had to figure out some pretty tricky
maneuvers to both
>> [music]
>> escape and attack the enemy. Maneuvers
I'm going to get a real taste for in
this gorgeous
Tiger Moth. [music]
She's an absolute beauty. Oh, she is.
Now, clearly
>> maneuver. a little bit younger than the
First World War, but to all intents and
purposes,
it's the same technology. Same sort of
thing. It's the same design, both open
cockpit biplanes, and just as
maneuverable as they were in the First
World War. Now, the advent of the
dogfight
and its relation to the invention of the
interrupter gear
is, I suppose, perhaps the most iconic
elements of the air war during the first
and the second World War.
>> It is really, yes. Yeah, that's right.
Everything they learned in the dogfights
of the First World War, they
transcribed, the Germans especially,
into the Second War. But, the maneuvers
that would have been required would have
put even more pressure on those early
airframes. Oh, yes, they would have
done. But, they were the airframes were
fairly strong, especially for turning
and looping maneuvers like that. They
could cope very well. What they couldn't
cope with was high-speed dives. In fact,
it wasn't until the advent of the SPAD,
which was was a French aircraft, and
then the British SE5 and the Camel came
along that were strong enough to take
that sort of pressure. But, I dare say
many pilots were lost figuring that out.
Let's face it, if you've got someone on
your tail and you can't outturn him,
you're going to try and dive to get away
from him. And you just hope your
airplane holds together. Now, the
dogfight demands some extraordinary
maneuvers from pilots. Give us an idea,
let's say, the top three that were
necessary that we can experience today.
The key maneuver, the one that everyone
knows, of course, is the Immelmann turn.
Where you got target aircraft here, and
you come down and attack from behind.
And for a long time, people thought the
Immelmann turn was a loop with a roll
off the top coming back this way, and
then he dived down. But, the airplane
that
Immelmann had, a Fokker Eindecker, only
had aileron only had wing warping
instead of ailerons. So, it hadn't got
the roll control to do that rolling
maneuver. Okay. And we suspect what he
probably did was pulled up and did a big
wingover like that, and then kind of
slipped back through the air, and yeah,
back down around this way. So, we'll
I'll demonstrate that to you,
and we'll see how that looks. So, the
Immelmann turn is the first. What's
next? The other one was the break into
the steep turn to come around sideways
into him that way. So, you fired your
guns, or rather, he's firing at you.
Yeah, or you fired at him once, you've
gone past him around like that, and then
he'll try and turn to get on your tail.
And you've turned inside him to try and
get inside him.
So you've got the two aircraft going
around round and round in a circle like
this. And the aircraft that can turn the
tightest is the one that's going to get
on the tail of the other one and shoot
him down. And the third one? The third
one was literally the break where
you're flying along, you're bounced by
someone else and you break away from it.
You break inside him.
Wow.
>> Part of the technique. Fascinating. And
you've got all of this sky to play with
today.
>> Yes, indeed. So three big maneuvers
we're going to have a go at. It's going
to be pretty chilly out there. It's very
cold out here on the ground.
>> Yes, let's go and get wrapped up.
>> Wrapped up, yeah. Yes, okay. [laughter]
And then we're going to do it.
Okay.
I'm about to take to the air in a
biplane that's over 80 years old to
experience not one, but three dog
fighting maneuvers from the First World
War.
On set. Contact.
Look at that. First ball. What a good
old boy.
And away we go.
Over up. Oh, that's great.
It's good to be able to be flying over
this unique First World War airfield.
So that is a Zeppelin's eye view of
their route to North London. That's
amazing.
So the first ever bit of wind up there.
Okay.
Here we go.
Take the first.
And then after that the break.
All right.
Oh, that's it.
Come on.
All right, come on.
>> [screaming]
>> Oh my gosh.
Woah.
Up.
That's my turn. Another one.
I have the utmost admiration
for those early pilots. I they just the
business of flying that they
avoiding or touching the enemy just
astonishing really.
We're going [music] into the steep turn.
So we start it. Oh,
there it is G.
Oh, there it is.
There it is.
Yep.
Yep, there it is.
Absolutely honest expects.
Oh my god.
And
that was a steep turn.
The next one is a break.
Okay.
That was a bit more of a violent
maneuver.
Okay, we're flying along. Okay, violent
maneuver again. Aircraft coming at us
from the right.
Okay, BREAKING RIGHT NOW.
WHOA!
OH MY GOD.
There's a G. [music]
Yep.
I cannot begin to imagine what it was
like having to execute those maneuvers
whilst the enemy was on your tail.
>> [music]
>> There we are. Power's coming off.
We are gliding down to this wonderful
ancient and oh so historic airfield,
Old Sarum Airfield.
Wow. Wow, Chris. If I can just
release my harness.
>> [laughter]
>> Um
astonishing, mate.
But how pilots were able to execute
those maneuvers at far greater speed
taking far more risks than we were
whilst trying to attack and escape the
enemy. And they had no armor plating or
anything. All they had was a sheet of
canvas protecting them. Well, that wing
over all the Immelmann turn
he certainly deserves to put his name to
that one. Did indeed. The only thing we
haven't done yet, mate, is have a cup of
tea. That's the best thing you've said
so far. Let's go and do it.
>> [laughter]
>> In many ways, aircraft were developing
[music] faster than the knowledge of how
to fly them. All the pilots that lost
their lives flying at Stow Maries did so
in accidents, but some did [music]
survive the war and went on to become
legends. This is the grave of Claude
Ridley.
>> [music]
>> He once was the commanding officer here.
He died 1942, a much decorated and fated
officer, but he chose to be buried
[music] here
amongst his former colleagues.
Although not as famous as some of the
other British pilots, aces like Edward
Mannock, James McCudden, or Albert Ball,
Claude Ridley's flying career was
spectacular. He had been wounded in the
foot in aerial combat
and he was brought back to this country
to recuperate. And as part of that
recuperation, he'd gone down to a small
airfield called Joyce Green. While he
was there and on patrol one evening, he
found a Zeppelin returning from a raid
on London along the Thames and he
managed to engage that Zeppelin with
some machine gun fire. It gradually
deflated and ended up in the in the
North Sea.
>> [music]
>> So, for that, he was awarded the
Military Cross. When he had recuperated,
he was sent back out to France.
>> [music]
>> He was part of the calvary of that
of officers, experienced officers, and
[music] the part of their duties was to
drop spies behind enemy lines. He would
normally reconnoiter an area the day
before knowing where the spy had to go.
He'd pick a spy up and then he would fly
him across the lines, find the area that
he'd reconnoitered the day before, drop
the spy off, and that was the end of his
mission. On the last occasion that he
was able to do [music] that, he found
that the engine on his aircraft failed.
[music]
So, both he and his spy on board had to
escape across the whole of occupied
Belgium. He made copious notes on what
was going on [music] behind German
lines. He was captured briefly on a
tram in Belgium, but managed to escape
from his guard again. He He jumped from
first-floor windows when the Germans
were were coming in the the bottom
ground floor.
Um and it was a whole boys' own
adventure escape. For all that
information that he brought back, he was
awarded the Distinguished Service Order.
He also got a private audience with King
George [music] V.
When he came here to take over the Home
Defense Flight at Stow Maries,
he was still 6 weeks short of his 20th
birthday.
So, uh effectively, he was commanding
the aerodrome and a whole flight at that
stage, aged 19, having already been
awarded the Distinguished Service
Service Order and the Military Cross.
Many First World War pilots from all
sides of the conflict became
celebrities. Their endeavors seemed more
alluring than those of their compatriots
on the ground. The hero worship
throughout the beginning of the First
World War started because aviation was
such a new subject. The young men that
did it appeared to be dashing,
especially the fighter pilots, and a
whole myth uh series of myths surrounded
uh what they were doing because nobody
really understood it. The most famous
example that everyone accepts now is uh
von Richthofen. His legend grew very
quickly during the war because the
Germans saw a huge propaganda uh use for
it with the news coming back from the
trenches being so utterly appalling and
the casualties in the trenches. I think
there was a a chance for the propaganda
machine on all sides to to kick in and
pick on the subject that would take the
public's mind possibly away from that.
But, if you can wrap it up in this aura
of gentlemanliness and being knights of
the air,
uh it has a much greater resonance with
the public than talking about sitting in
the trench and the mere slaughter of
what was going on.
You know, wandering around Stow Maries,
you get a real sense of the ghosts of
yesteryear. Take this place. This looks
like a pretty innocuous farm building
and in many ways, that's what it became
when the airfield actually closed down.
But this used to be
the officers' mess. Try and imagine it
with a beautiful veranda out here. And
of course,
including much more salubrious
surroundings [music] than it does today.
This, believe it or not,
was the bar. Look, there's one of the
original doors still [music]
on its hinges. Through there was the
dining room,
complete with fireplace in here. You can
imagine some of the parties that this
room
would have seen and heard during its
years of occupation. And then through
here, through what would have been a
lovely set
>> [music]
>> of French doors, is a room that I think
is particularly moving. This
was the quiet room of the mess. This was
a place where pilots would come and
reflect on their day-to-day lives and of
course, on the dangers they were facing
and I suppose on many of their friends
that they had lost during the campaign.
All of this
is due to be conserved [music]
and it's worth it because so much of it
does survive. Look, the original
ceiling, the beams, that lovely
Dutch brick fireplace. [music] But my
goodness me,
what a job it is.
Stow Maries' location was deemed
unsuitable for a World War II airfield
and it was abandoned.
Its buildings were used for agricultural
purposes and nature began to take over.
In 2009, the site was auctioned and
bought by Russell Savery and his
business partner with the promise that
they would restore it to its former
glory.
All right, what we got here, Joe, is the
washroom. [music]
So, I've got the original top for this,
but we just removed it, but that would
have had the wooden top there. The
lovely little
porcelain
hand wash basins with a Royal Flying
Corps emblem on. I presume that up here
lots of coat hooks
>> Yeah, it would have been the coats,
yeah, absolutely. And then coming
through into here, we've got the the
bathroom. So, four bars, you've got one
over there, there, one there and there.
And then we have the partitioning. We've
got some little bit of the pipe work.
And we've also got the the boiler room,
which is which is next door. What's
remarkable is that you can absolutely
see this place 100 years ago, can't you?
Oh, absolutely. It is just a fantastic
story. And with these buildings, I just
treat them as a book, you know, they've
all got a fantastic story to tell, each
individual building, all 22 of them. But
how did you first discover Stow Maries?
It was the internet and looking for a
workshop premises. And it said it old
aerodrome for sale, which obviously my
ears pricked up at that, and came to
visit it. Fell in love with it in 5
minutes flat.
And there our journey started for the
conservation of aerodrome. But did you
then realize that you were letting
yourself in for a huge conservation
project?
>> It's a bigger project than I've ever
ever done before, but it is very well
worthwhile to tell the history of the
Royal Flying Corps, the importance of
that. Much is known about trench warfare
and the sacrifices made there, but not
so much is known about the Royal Flying
Corps and these pioneers of early flight
and the problems and things that they
had with their aircraft failing and that
sort of thing. So, it's it's a very
important that we keep that part of the
history going. But Russell, I have been
constantly astonished as to how much of
this Stow Maries still survives. I mean,
it's languished here for 100 years and I
get the feeling that it's sort of
been waiting for the right man, the
right opportunity to come along and now
you're it.
>> [laughter]
>> Thank you.
It's going to be a fairly large project
and I think I'm just looking at as the
Johnny Cash song really, which is one
piece at a time, so you don't get too
overwhelmed by it. But when this is
done, when it's
finally conserved, will it be as
sumptuous
and as elegant as it might have been
once a time.
>> Yeah, this officer's mess is going to be
the jewel in the crown that we have. And
there's one favorite room back here I'd
like to take you to. Please do. Yeah, I
mean you can take me around here all day
long. It's brilliant.
So what we got here is that was the main
entrance into the mess from the
officer's quarters. So it'd be very busy
through this corridor.
>> So this was the main sort of spine of
the building. It is indeed, yes. Coming
through into the dining room. And my
favorite little room really of the whole
building. So this is the mess orderly's
office here. And the guys would have
been coming up here and signing their
mess bills. I mean unusual to have a
kind of sash window inside. In a way
we've caught it at a moment in time,
haven't we? Because it looks like it's
open for business. And there an original
desk.
>> We have one in the back as well. So
there's a nice little back office there.
And
the reason this is important cuz this is
a
part of the building that I bring some
of the relatives to that are of older
pilots because all of their officer
pilots would have been in front of this
window and signing their mess orderly
um sheet. You can you can kind of taste
the atmosphere here. I know it wasn't
operational for very long, but it's so
complete. It's such a a time capsule.
Yeah, it is indeed. I mean that's what
that's the important that's why we have
to keep it. We've got 22 original
buildings here now. There were 51
buildings in total. So majority of those
were wooden buildings. So they would
just be erected.
They are going to be exactly as they
were. We have the original drawings. We
managed to get drawings of the hangars
from Hendon.
So they will be done exactly as they
were. But when it's finished, Russell,
this will be a mecca for anyone
interested in First World War aviation.
Not just in Britain, but I guess in
Europe as well. You're absolutely right.
I mean we will have aircraft here which
will fly. So they won't be just purely
museum pieces. Camels, SE5s, BE2s. And
we have actually some of those coming
shortly.
So it's going to be an absolute
fantastic place, a jewel in the crown I
think for the UK. You'll have many
people come from Europe and indeed
America as well. You've got plenty to
do. We have. Just get on with it. All
right. [laughter]
Russell's [music] plan is to first
restore the existing brick buildings
needing immediate attention before
constructing the wooden buildings
including hangars.
These hangars will house operational
World War I aircraft which will complete
Stow Maries' resurrection.
Stow Maries is an inspiring and poignant
reminder of those early days of military
aviation and of course of the men and
the machines that laid the foundations
>> [music]
>> for its future.
At the outbreak of war, we possessed
just 90 aircraft. By its end 4 years
later, over 20,000 had been produced.
[music]
And in recognizing the value of aircraft
as weapons of war, just 7 months before
the end of the conflict [music] in 1918,
the RAF was formed. And the rest, as
they say,
is history. [music]
>> [music]
[music]
>> For over a century,
the legendary tales that have surrounded
our great British airfields have
inspired generations of people including
me. Which is why I am on a personal
mission to cross the UK to visit some of
our most important airfields to
understand not just about their
contribution to our past, but
importantly how many of them have helped
define our future.
From the UK's first flight [music]
through to groundbreaking innovation
such as carbon fiber and the jet engine
and the extraordinary effort spent on
preserving our aviation [music]
heritage, join me as I explore the story
of the airfields that have helped shape
Britain and the world.
>> The age of the long-range bomber is
arguably over as missiles and smaller
multi-role aircraft have taken its
place, but the story of the RAF bomber
itself is a long and illustrious one.
And few airfields are as perhaps
connected to that story as here, RAF
Coningsby. First opened in 1940, it's
played a key role in the frontline
defense of the United Kingdom for over
70 years.
Perhaps the most famous British bomber
of all time was the Avro Lancaster. No
bomber before it or since has been as
successful. And at the end of the Second
World War, the head of Bomber Command,
Air Chief Marshal Sir Arthur Harris,
wrote to the makers, Avro.
I should say this to those who put that
shining sword in our hand. Without your
genius and your efforts, we would not
have prevailed, for I believe the
Lancaster to be the greatest single
factor in winning the war. Today, there
is only one left flying in Britain, and
it's here at RAF Coningsby.
>> [music]
>> Roger.
Hello, Jules. Very nice to see you.
>> Pleasure to meet you.
I'm like a child in a sweet shop. This
is the most incredible hangar. It's full
of one of everything I would ever want
to take home with me.
The Battle of Britain Memorial Flight is
such an institution.
How did it come about? A group of uh
guys decided that there there should be
something that uh that celebrated the
Battle of Britain uh and to remember
those uh you know, brave few that uh
that gave their lives um for uh for the
country. So, there was four Spitfires
started the flight and then from there
onwards it's it's grown and grown and
grown. So, now we have two Hurricanes,
six Spitfires,
Dakota, Lancaster and two Chipmunks.
Being surrounded by this fabulous
collection, it's hard and unfair in a
way to try and pick a favorite, but I'm
going to stick my neck out. Now, for me
the most iconic aircraft of the Second
World War has to be the Lancaster and
you get to fly it. What made it so
special? As you say, you know, she is a
an iconic shape in the sky
you know, iconic sound of four Merlins
as well. We needed a heavy bomber to to
accomplish what the other bombers
weren't doing. It was sort of born out
of a design which was the Manchester
first off which wasn't a very successful
aircraft. It it had lots of problems and
it was plagued with with all sorts of
troubles. Roy Chadwick who designed it
then said actually what we need to do is
get more power to it and make it bigger
and beef it up and then it'll be exactly
the machine you want. Well, I am itching
to take a closer look.
>> [music]
>> You're the best man to show me around,
Roger.
Come in and
welcome to the Lanc. This is amazing.
So, remind me of the crew. How many?
Working from the back then you have the
tail gunner right at the back.
>> Yeah. Then the mid upper.
Then working forwards you've got a
signaler
as well and then you have the the flight
deck crew of air engineer, navigator and
pilot. And then forward of that you've
got bomb aimer as well
and the bomb aimer would double up
sometimes as the the forward gunner as
well.
And the thing that strikes me Roger is
that
I'm wearing civilian clothes. I'm not
wearing a wartime flying suit or a
parachute. The idea of trying to move
through this fuselage in a hurry to try
and rescue a friend when you operate
this machinery or you play loud. It's
hard to imagine, isn't it?
It is, yeah. And it is it's a tight
space. It's you know, it's it's a small
space because the business of this
aircraft is all about the bombs and the
weapons. So you know, as you can see
it's it's quite big on the outside but
very small on the inside. Just as
something of interest is that the the
distance from the ammo box to the tail
gunner is 9 yd. So the expression of
giving the full 9 yd
comes from a you know, a length of ammo
being shot by the tail gunner. I love
stories like that. It's the sort of
thing I remember long into my dotage.
But keeping this aircraft in the air is
an enormous challenge. You're having to
revisit and relearn many of those tricks
and skills that maintenance crews would
have taken as second nature I suppose 70
years ago.
Yeah, and there is you know, there's
obviously going to be elements of skill
fade but but the person who you really
want to speak to is one of our
engineers.
Jules, let me introduce you to Gary one
of our engineers. Gary Hello, nice to
meet you. Gary, nice to see you.
This is fabulous. This is proper
engineering. Are these genuine
blueprints? They are genuine blueprints,
yeah. So he here gets to fly it and
occasionally
break it.
Challenge it.
>> [laughter]
>> And you have to keep it up there flying
around for all to see and enjoy. Yeah.
How difficult a job is it?
It can be difficult at times. I mean the
main problems we have is finding spares
at short notice. But of course you can't
just go and draw a new part off the
shelf as you would have done
during the 40s. Do you have to
manufacture a lot of parts? We do have
to manufacture a lot of parts now.
But as long as we've got the original
drawing and an original material specs,
we can have anything made. How long have
you been working on on Lancasters for?
I've actually done 11 years in total.
Wow. I have been back working on uh
Tornadoes and Typhoons in between, but I
managed to come back. I definitely
prefer working on the Lancaster and the
the aircraft that we've got here.
It's engineering it is grassroots.
It's what I joined up to do and uh if
you work on a Typhoon,
uh computers tend to tell you what's
wrong with it and you're just changing
boxes a lot of the time. Whereas here,
we get the drawings out and we get
things made. So, having spent months
stripping it all down and putting it
back together again,
do you get to have a ride? Does he take
you for a spin? He does give us a spin.
We uh we do get to fly in the Lancaster,
uh which is a massive privilege uh
being on the flight. Brilliant. That's a
perk worth having, isn't it? Gary, thank
you very much indeed. We'll leave you to
your very technical drawings and we'll
continue our tour, shall we, Roger?
Thank you.
>> have a look at the front.
Well, Jules, welcome to my world. This
is where
I get the best view of things. This is
your office. This is amazing. This is my
office, yes. It looks, needless to say,
incredibly complicated up here, Roger.
Is it a delicate aircraft to fly?
Because pilots did say they loved it.
It's not a delicate aircraft to fly. Um
you do have to manhandle her around the
skies. Um but because you do actively
fly her around the skies, that's part of
the the appeal, that's part of the love
for flying her. Well, Roger, it's been
an absolute treat to take such a close
look at this aircraft and it's perfectly
clear that both in the air and on the
ground, she is in very, very good hands.
Thank you very much. In 1941, just as
the first Lancasters were being tested
by Avro, an inquiry was commissioned
into the accuracy of Bomber Command.
What it revealed was that [music] on a
routine mission such as those carried
out by aircraft from RAF Coningsby, only
one in five aircraft were capable
[music] of dropping their bombs within
five miles of the target. It wasn't
proving to be the strategically decisive
weapon
>> [music]
>> that Churchill had envisaged.
In February 1942, the man charged with
turning Bomber Command into an effective
task force was Sir Arthur Harris.
He envisaged massive raids using an
organized approach to direct the bombers
over [music] their targets.
On the night of the 30th of May 1942,
1,047 bombers headed towards [music] the
German city of Cologne.
The results were devastating. Only 3% of
the bombers that took part were lost and
a large percentage of targets were
destroyed. Harris was able to
demonstrate [music] how effectively a
large bomber force could inflict crucial
damage.
Two more subsequent [music] operations
to Essen and Bremen became known as the
thousand bomber raids.
As a result, Bomber Command received
increased resources allowing them to
play a crucial role in the final Allied
victory.
The most famous squadron [music] to fly
from Coningsby was 617, otherwise known
as the Dambusters. Later on in the war,
[music] they moved to Woodhall Spa and
this, the Petwood House Hotel, became
their officers' mess. They were an elite
bunch specifically formed to deliver the
brainchild of pioneering aviation
engineer Barnes Wallis.
Rob.
Hello, mate. Nice to see you.
Look at this place. It's stuffed to the
rafters with 617 memorabilia. Well,
welcome to the spiritual home of 617
Squadron. Now, the walls are plastered
in images of the squadron and its
exploits and of course their heroes as
well. And over there, Barnes Wallis. And
in a way, we can't talk about 617
without starting with Wallis because
without him, it wouldn't have existed.
Certainly, because the squadron was
formed specifically for one operation
initially and that was to deliver his
bouncing bomb. He was a remarkable
engineer. I noticed on the way in you've
got some drawings of the bomb. Can we
take a closer look and try and
understand how it worked and what he was
trying to do?
>> Well, he was a remarkable engineer. I
mean, he'd started off life just before
the First World War um
having been a marine engineer, he
switched to designing airships.
What encouraged him to start thinking
about munitions?
Well, the thing was that he wanted to
find a way of making a contribution to
the war and he thought, well, how best
can an engineer bring the war to a rapid
end? Now, before the war, the Air
Ministry and the RAF had been looking at
various targets and amongst the targets
they'd looked at sources of power, but
all the sources of power, be it coal
mines or dams and that, simply too
massive to be damaged by bombs of that
period which were relatively small and
relatively ineffective.
But Wallis latched onto this and he
thought, well, let's take a
uh a target like a dam.
How can we actually knock a dam down?
And his first idea was to create a very
large bomb, a bomb of 10 tons, but then
experimentation showed that even a large
bomb dropped relatively close to the dam
still wouldn't do it. And after that,
they then found that a a much smaller
charge, but it placed directly in
contact with the dam wall would would
actually do the job. So, you didn't need
a big bomb, you just needed a small bomb
and you needed to get it in contact with
the dam wall and that was the problem.
And that was the challenge to get the
bomb
into such a specific position that it
could do its work against the dam.
>> Absolutely. And that's how he devised
the bouncing bomb. It is the most
unconventional looking bomb in many
respects. How difficult a job
was it for Wallis to sell this to the
Air Ministry?
Well, you imagine, bearing in mind that
the damage rate hasn't happened and all
this is isn't history yet. And someone
comes along to you and says,
"I've got this idea for a 4 and 1/2 ton
bomb, and I can make it bounce across
the surface of a reservoir, and and hit
a target."
I mean, you're going to think that
that's just another one of those
crackpot schemes, isn't it?
The idea behind the bouncing bomb, known
as Upkeep, was to deliver a charge to
the base of a German dam, where it would
cause the most damage.
In theory, if dropped at a certain
speed, angle, and point on the lake,
Upkeep would bounce along the water, hop
over the torpedo nets, hit the dam, sink
straight down to the optimal depth for
[music] destruction, and detonate.
Well, this all looks a little bit Heath
Robinson, Rob. Well, I mean, it is in
many respects, but this is exactly how
Wallis started out testing his theory,
which developed into the bouncing bomb.
So, we've got a tin bath full of water,
a string suspended between two canes,
and a table at the far end. What are you
going
Well, really, in order to develop his
idea, first thing Wallis needed to do,
apart from making to establish whether
or not you could actually bounce
something off water, but he needed to
establish the law of ricochet, prove
that it could be done consistently. So,
what you've got to do is you've got to
imagine that here is a catapult.
>> So, I'm the catapult.
>> He took his missile, which for which he
used one of his daughter's marbles, All
right. and placed it in the catapult,
fired it at a low angle, the intention
being to ricochet it off the surface of
the water, over
the string, to land on the table.
And he's looking to find a formula
that's going to predict that
consistently. Exactly. What he's trying
to do is to have a experiment he can
replicate in order to calculate the
basically the law of ricochet. And for
that, he simply needs a number of
inputs, which is the
the the force or the speed of the of the
of the marble being projected, the
height at which it bounces, which he can
determine by the string, and then the
distance that the bounce has taken. So,
from those he can actually calculate the
the curve of trajectory. And by doing
that and
varying the inputs, he can come up with
the mathematical formula he's looking
for. It is remarkable though when you
think about it, from such humble
beginnings this very simple experiment
is transformed in the mind of this
incredibly talented and dedicated
engineer into what becomes arguably the
most audacious air raid of the war.
Really, the the
the crunch comes on the eve of the
operation when the squadron had been
told for the first time what they're
going to do. And Wallis stands in front
of them and explains the weapon. I'm
sure there must have been some element
going through his mind of say of of
thinking, I hope my calculations are
correct. But they were going out to
conduct the ultimate experiment I
suppose in the mind of the scientist.
Yes, I mean you could put it that way
and it was an experiment over which he
had no control. But the raid was on.
The raid was on.
>> [music]
>> On the night of the 16th of May, 1943,
19 Lancasters left for Germany. 617
Squadron were entrusted with the task of
crippling three [music] key German dams,
the Möhne, the Eder, and the Sorpe.
The attack was called [music] Operation
Chastise and utilized the ingenious
bouncing bomb designed by Wallis.
There's five crews of which we were one
were briefed for the Sorpe. [music]
And of course, the Sorpe had to be
different.
It didn't have any towers. [music]
So, there's no sighting to go trade.
It was so placed in the hills that a a
head-on attack would be very difficult,
in fact, almost impossible. The first
thing we noticed was that on the hill
through down which we're supposed to
make the attack, [music]
There's a church spire halfway down. So,
Joe said, "Right, I'm using that as a
marker." [music]
And use that to line up the aircraft as
best he could on the target.
If I wasn't satisfied, I called dummy
run.
If Joe wasn't satisfied,
he'd just [music] pull away and left me
to call dummy run.
And it was at stage, after about the
sixth or seventh [music] of these,
and Dave Rodger came up with, "Won't
somebody get that bomb out of here?" I
had to realize how to become the most
unpopular member of crew in double-quick
time.
But there we were.
So, on the 10th run,
we were down to 30 ft. And when I said,
"Bombs gone."
"Thank Christ." came [music] from the
rear turret.
But [snorts] then,
with being so low, it was nose up
straight away.
So, I didn't see the explosion.
But Dave did.
And he estimated [music]
that the water went up to about 1,000
ft.
We looked around
and we had crumbled the top of the dam.
Distance of about 10 [music] yd.
Barnes Wallis had told us
that because of the structure of the
[music] Sorpe,
it would take at least six bombs
to crack it.
If you can crack it,
the water pressure will do the rest. And
judging from the amount of water in that
dam, yes, I'm sure he was right.
Operation [music] Chastise breached the
Möhne and the Eder dams and damaged the
Sorpe, but the losses were high.
Out of the 19 Lancasters that took
[music] part, three had to turn back,
leaving just 16 to complete the mission.
Of those, eight were lost
along with 56 aircrew.
As far as the raid itself is concerned,
yes,
it was a success.
It proved to Hitler
and the German hierarchy
that what they thought was impregnable,
the Royal Air Force could get through
and destroy.
And it meant that
>> [music]
>> the skilled workmen
that were working on a
anti-invasion wall along the coast
had to be withdrawn to work on the
repair of the dams.
But I think the greatest
advantage
was the morale effect it had on the
people of this country. I was one of the
lucky ones in the right crew, [music] in
the right time, in the right place, and
equally lucky to get back.
The military effectiveness [music]
of Operation Chastise has long been
debated, but its value as a propaganda
tool and as a morale booster cannot be
denied. And perhaps most importantly of
all, it gave the British public hope
that after nearly 4 years of fighting,
at last the tide of the war could be
turning in their favor.
Rob, after the success of
the Dambusters raid and the bouncing
bomb,
Wallis is very moved by the loss of life
amongst the air crews that took part,
isn't he? Very much so. He'd stood in
front of the crews that were going off
to do the operation. He'd spoken to
them. He'd seen them in front of him.
And then, of course, the following
morning he saw, in effect, the empty
tables and realized the the human cost
of the development in his weapon in
terms of air crew lives.
And he was extremely moved by this. But
it doesn't put him off, and he goes on
to develop bigger, better munitions. Now
ably supported by the head of Bomber
Command, Air Chief Marshal Sir Arthur
Harris, who, let's face it, was pretty
skeptical about the bouncing bomb.
Harris has allegedly
turned to him after the operation and
said, "Well, Wallis, I didn't believe a
word that you told me, but now you could
sell sell me a pink elephant." And in
fact, here we actually have, I suppose,
what you might call the pink elephant.
>> This is it. Is this the famous Tallboy?
That's right. Wallis reverted back to
his original concept of a large bomb
that would penetrate deep in in into the
ground causing an earthquake effect and
Harris had in fact given him the green
light to go ahead and develop this. So,
here we have it. This is Tallboy. It's a
12,000 lb deep penetration bomb. The
concept being that dropped from high
altitude, it's a very heavy bomb. It
will hit the hit the ground and
penetrate deeply underground before
exploding. And then when it detonates,
the shockwave will travel through the
earth and shake any structure in the
vicinity. But Rob, I suppose in many
ways the development of this particular
bomb once again continues this now
established relationship between 617
Squadron and the mind of Wallis. The two
things are absolutely interdependent
upon each other. Very much so, yes.
And of course
it was it was from here at Woodhall Spa
that the squadron carried out its
operations using Wallis's bombs uh
Tallboy and Grand Slam. Initially, the
first attack was made against the
railway tunnel which proved the
earth-moving qualities of the weapon. It
then went on to be used against U-boat
pens, V-weapon sites, and of course
Germany's most fearsome battleship
Tirpitz. Rob, how would you assess the
legacy
of Wallis's contribution to the war
effort? Well, it was certainly
significant in that Wallis provided
Bomber Command with the weapons to
destroy major targets which they would
otherwise been unable to destroy. And at
the same time, Bomber Command provided
Wallis with a way of delivering those
weapons with precision in the form of
617 Squadron.
Second only to the attrition suffered by
U-boat crews, serving in Bomber Command
was arguably the most dangerous
profession of the war.
Of 125,000
air crew who served, some 55,000 [music]
lost their lives. It's an enormous
figure equal to the population of a
small town. Here at Coningsby Cemetery
in amongst the Commonwealth war graves
is one that is dedicated to an unknown
airman. And it serves as a poignant
reminder to all of those who lost their
lives throughout six years of the aerial
campaign.
Following the success of the bouncing
bomb, Barnes Wallace returned to
developing even larger weapons.
These would allow bombers from RAF
Coningsby and other airbases to target
reinforced structures like U-boat pens
and secret rocket sites.
Wallace produced deep penetration
earthquake bombs. First, the Tallboy at
6 tons and then the Grand Slam at 10.
Now, to really understand the physics
and the mechanics [music] behind the
earthquake or the Tallboy bomb, you
really need to somehow see it in action.
Now, of course, we don't have a real one
that [music] we can just let off, but we
can get close to it. So, I have enlisted
the help of my old mate Tony Lewis, a
man whose passion for military history
is equaled only by his passion for
pyrotechnics. If anyone can [music] help
us make a bang, it's him.
Nice and square. Tony.
Hello, Wallace. How are you doing? I'm
very well, mate. How are you? Not bad. A
little bit Mutt and Jeff these days, but
You're the Jeff. All right. How are your
fingers? Uh all there.
So, everything's going well. Now, tell
me, what is going on here?
What we're doing is we're building a
structure to help to show the effects of
the blast and overpressure from uh
in this case a 500-lb general purpose
bomb that would have been used in carpet
bombing.
And uh what we're going to show is that
a surface blast wouldn't knock down a
structure a structure of this type. But
an earthquake bomb would. It certainly
would. So, this is a typical structure
you might find supporting a bridge, a
railway, that sort of thing. So, why
wouldn't a conventional bomb shatter
this in a way that an earthquake bomb
might have done? Well, we can show you
that.
I've got a small version here. What's
this from? Uh this is actually a a Stuka
uh fragmentation bomb. The thing with
this type of bomb is when it hits the
ground, it explodes. And so, all the
explosive energy
is uh is dissipated into the atmosphere.
We'll get a small crater, okay, a
reasonable crater, but most of the
energy's gone, gone into the atmosphere.
Brilliant. Well, we've got to finish
building this then. Okay. Yeah, if you
don't mind, grab your small blocks and
we will uh we'll complete it. Ah.
It's like a sort of giant Jenga, isn't
it? Yeah. Well, there's some weight to
this. I mean, it's not going to blow
over in the wind, is it? No.
Right then. Last one's, Tony. You get
the privilege of that. Okay.
There we go.
So, how big a charge are you going to
put next to this to simulate a 500-lb
bomb? Okay. Obviously, this is a model
of a structure. So, we're going to do a
scaled-down version. We're going to use
half a kilo of TNT.
And that will simulate the effect of a
general-purpose bomb, okay?
Exploding above surface, you'll see the
shockwave uh propagate
and you'll see that the uh the tower
will
still be there.
You are so confident.
I love it, Tony. I love your confidence.
You haven't let me down in the past,
mate.
>> No, I won't let you down this time,
mate. Right then. Let's get on with
stage one and detonate our 500-pounder.
Let's do it.
Okay, Jules, here we go. This is the
firing point. Ah, this is what I'm
after. Okay, get your
ear defenders on.
Let's have a concrete wall between us
and that. Yes, definitely. Perfect,
mate. I like this, [music] Tony. This is
very old school. Yes, it's German Second
World War. You're joking. It's just
ideal for the job. It was designed for
bridge demolition, etc. Only you would
have one of those.
>> Ah, she's my little baby.
>> [snorts]
>> Okay, we'll wind her up. Yep.
Okay.
You good? Good. Okay, stand by.
3 2 1
I didn't see any fits. No. No. I think I
think she'll still be standing. I say
she's still standing. I'm not.
Well, she's still there, Jules. I owe
you a pint.
And as you could see,
pretty much like a general purpose bomb
would do, it's dug a a crater. Certain
amount has hit the the tower. You've got
a certain amount of debris.
>> Yeah, there's a bit of grass up there,
look.
>> Yeah. And it all smells a bit of
explosive, actually, and fuel. And you
can see where it sort of charred it
somewhat and the and the grass around it
But you can see what a challenge Bomber
Command faced when trying to take out
targets like this, even with hundreds,
thousands of conventional bombs. You can
get close to it, but actually not really
scratch it. And even if you did hit it,
you know, it didn't tend to blow the
structure to pieces. It would blow a
piece off it. Well, I can't wait to see
what your tall boy will do to this
concrete tower, Tony. Uh I think you'll
find it's not standing.
>> [laughter]
>> Well, listen, I've already lost a pint
so far. I'm not going to bet again.
Well,
I'll settle on a nice steak and kidney
pie for this one.
>> All right, you're on. I'll go with it.
The effect of a 500-lb general purpose
bomb used in carpet bombing would only
create [music] a surface blast.
What Wallis did was to take it a step
further, producing bombs that would go
deeper into the earth before exploding,
[music]
creating an earthquake effect underneath
the structure.
So let's see how well our tower fares
with this explosion.
So, what I want you to do first is we
need to to prime up the exploder. So, if
you can if you can wind that up until it
comes to a stop.
It's quite a a strong spring.
Here we go.
A Tallboy
underneath a pile of concrete blocks.
Stand by.
3 2 1
Excellent.
There is all I certainly no chance that
that is still there.
Oh my goodness me. Look at that.
That's astonishing. Not only is the
tower not standing, but look at the Look
at the debris. Oh, everything All being
lifted out of the ground.
Okay, and did you feel the shockwave
coming through the ground towards us?
>> Oh, yeah. And this is a tiny handful of
TNT.
>> Yeah. Not 22,000 lb worth of it.
So, you can imagine
in scale
a very similar effect to what the
Tallboy would give. I didn't expect a
hole this big. Yes, we've got some
filling in to do.
>> [laughter]
>> But, how did the bomb itself not explode
on impact? How did it get so deep
underground before going off? Barnes
Wallis, very clever man.
He used Torpex, which is a very powerful
explosive, but also a stable explosive
cuz so it could withstand the impact of
hitting the ground and not going off
through the shock.
He also used a hardened uh bomb casing,
okay, that would withstand hitting the
ground and penetrated it without
shattering the the casings. And he also
used the height
and the aerodynamics of to bomb,
which would travel over 700 mph. So,
he's breaking the sound barrier.
>> It's incredible, isn't it? Yeah. And as
you can see from this, it's not a case
of hitting the structure.
It's better just just to miss, okay? And
then rely on the shockwave traveling
through the ground to bring the
structure to the ground. And you can
really see that. A finer demonstration,
Tony, I could not have hoped for. I'm
proud of myself. Come on, then.
I'll sort you out with that finer point,
though.
Maybe some chips and peas?
Wish you luck with that, though.
The years following the Second World War
saw political and military tension
between the East and West grow,
resulting in the Cold War. [music]
It was also a time of rapid development
in technology with the advancement of
the jet engine and nuclear weapons.
>> [music]
>> It was a combination of these that
culminated in Britain's V bombers, the
Valiant, the Vulcan, and the Victor.
Three jet-powered monsters designed to
carry Britain's nuclear weapons.
In 1962, with the Cold War reaching its
climax, Coningsby welcomed its first
squadron of Vulcans, and they were
housed in these very distinctive Gaydon
hangars, notable because of those huge
double doors to accommodate the Vulcan's
enormous tail fin. And the hangar itself
is a great demonstration of the
difference in scale between the Vulcan
and one of the RAF's modern multi-role
aircraft. Now, there is today only one V
bomber, as they were known, left flying,
the XH558.
The Vulcan is quite a different aircraft
to a lot of aircraft, and it's a big
airplane,
but it has very very powerful controls.
So, even though the aircraft is about
the size of an Airbus airliner,
it flies and feels more like a fighter.
So, we've got very powerful flight
controls, and we have a we have a
control stick
rather than a control column, which you
might expect in a big airplane. The
Vulcan was first manufactured in 1952
and was the backbone of the UK's
airborne nuclear deterrent. [music]
From 1957 to 1969, it stood by for 24
hours a day, armed with nuclear weapons,
ready to take off within 2 minutes of a
Soviet attack.
Luckily, it was [music] never called
into action. The Vulcan naturally is
going to eventually stop flying. Um
unlike us with a vintage car where you
can keep driving the car over and over
providing you pass the MOT, airplanes
have a a finite life. I feel uh very
privileged to fly the Vulcan. There's
only this one Vulcan flying in the
world. And there's only a handful of us
that actually fly the aircraft. So, I'm
very lucky to to to that end.
I will be very sad when we stop flying
her.
RAF Coningsby was the base for three
operational squadrons of Vulcans during
the 1960s, but more technological
advances meant they were replaced. The
last airworthy Vulcan is maintained and
flown by members of the Vulcan to the
Sky Trust in Doncaster.
Wow.
Look at that.
You know, each year that passes could be
the [music] last that this incredible
Vulcan is kept in the air, but to look
after it and maintain it to such a high
standard is, as you can appreciate, an
ongoing struggle, which is why I've come
to meet the engineers [music]
who make it all possible. And as you can
see, to offer them my humble services.
It's also a brilliant excuse to get my
hands dirty.
Ah, tough.
Hello, mate. How are you?
Good to see you. Nice to have. Wow, you
can smell the fuel. What are you doing?
Um during the winter, what we're doing
is replacing a couple of the fuel drain
traps. Uh we need to test the fuel every
so often for any water and reseating
them now and again. You've been working
on these aircraft for how long? Uh over
on and off over 30 years now. Done 26
years in the RAF. Joined up as a young
lad and come out to training straight
onto the Vulcans.
>> So, you remember what it was like, what
the atmosphere was like for the ground
crews and the air crews when these were
a nuclear deterrent? Yes, sir. I was
still working on the aircraft. In fact,
one of the jobs as an electrician was
actually test out the nuclear systems.
What I find astonishing is the
relatively short period of time between
the Lancaster, say, and this. It is as
completely new as straight back end of
the Second World War. It was designed by
the same people who done the Lancaster,
and there's only 11 years difference
between the flight test of the Lancaster
and the flight test of the Vulcan. Now,
look, I'm kitted up. We're ready to go.
I'm happy to get as mucky as you like.
What are you up to here again? We're
just replacing one of the uh the fuel
drain valves. And what you can do, if
you like, you can fit the new one. You
make it a little bit Yeah, that's the
new one there. Is Is that something
that's brand new? Did you have to make
that? No, we've actually got this from
one of the manufacturers. And in fact,
there's a label in here, look. Come from
the overhaul back in 1989 when they
bought the airplane off as scrap value
when it was sold off in uh '93. They
bought I'd say over 600 tons of spares.
So, luckily, we do have a spare one of
these. So, what's the trick then, Tev?
Well, the trick is we'll take the cap
off.
Put the new washer on for you. And if
you'd like, you get yourself some gloves
and glasses.
>> Oh, yeah. You can fit it.
If you think you're clever enough. Well,
you know what? I'm a shocker for
over-tightening things.
We don't want to get it cross-threaded,
do we? Cuz otherwise, we'll have to
>> we need to do. Retap
>> Otherwise, you'll just ground a 10
million pound airplane. And there'll be
around about 200,000 people who won't
see it next year. Yeah, there's no
pressure there. No, no pressure at all.
Yeah, but just come up this ladder here.
That'll be the easiest one for you to go
up.
Gosh, look at all I mean, all of these
avionics, all of these pipes and
anodized parts. I mean,
it is incredible the amount of equipment
and paraphernalia that goes into keeping
even what appear to be the simplest
systems running. There's yet all the
various fuel supply pipes that into and
out of the fuel tanks and that's what
supplies the engines. So, I'm just
putting that straight into that.
>> Yeah, into that hole.
Now, I don't want fuel running down my
wrist. I don't know if it There we go.
There we go. Right.
There's the fuel.
She's in. She's in. How about that? Hey.
Now, that
>> an engineer out of you yet.
There we are. Brilliant. There you are.
You have helped service
>> [laughter]
>> the last flying Vulcan in the world.
Well, I just I'm astounded that this
aircraft
is still flying and when you look at the
minutiae of what has to happen to keep
it in the air, I think it's a not just a
credit to you, but also a credit to its
design. Well, it is iconic. It's the
unique shape of it and it's it's the
size, the power and as I say, when seen
heard and felt when you are maximum
power, it's never forgot. If this wasn't
available to play with, what would you
do with yourself? Probably have to find
a proper job.
>> [laughter]
>> Well, you're doing a great job with this
so mate. Thank you very much indeed.
>> Thank you.
Thankfully, the V bombers were never
used for their intended purpose, but in
many ways you could argue that they
fulfilled their brief. They helped
prevent the outbreak of a nuclear war by
acting as a very potent nuclear
deterrent. The only time the Vulcan
would ever fly in anger was during the
Falklands War in 1982.
When the Vulcan was tasked with a
conventional bombing mission to take out
runways and radar stations.
It would be the last mission flown by
this iconic aircraft.
There are no longer any heavy bombers
based at Coningsby or indeed the rest of
the UK, but fear not. These bomb proof
Cold War hangers are now home to
something else, something far more
potent.
The Eurofighter Typhoon.
>> [music]
>> This is it. Arguably the most capable
aircraft the RAF has ever possessed. And
it just goes to show what can happen if
you lock aero engineers from Germany,
Italy, Spain, and Britain in a room and
leave them there for long enough.
[music] That's exactly what they did
back in 1988, and this is what they came
up with 15 years later. Much of its
design is still top secret. That red bag
on the front there, that's covering up
the air intake. I'm not allowed to show
it to you. It's that sensitive. It can
carry a suite of weapons. You name it,
it can do it. Air-to-air,
air-to-surface. And here, this is the
business end. Two EJ200 engines, each
one developing some 20,000 [music] lb of
thrust. That means the Eurofighter can
travel at 1.8 Mach. That's nearly twice
the speed of sound. It really is a
phenomenal piece of engineering.
And when you consider what 100 years ago
we were just about getting into the air,
look where we've come.
This is the future. This is
the 21st century fighter in all its
glory.
There are between 40 and 50 Typhoons at
Coningsby at any one time,
>> [music]
>> belonging to four RAF squadrons.
Well, Justin, that's the future, isn't
it? The Typhoon.
>> Yeah. We no longer talk about heavy
bombers in terms of the RAF's infantry.
What brought about their decline? We've
gone away from heavy bombers as such. Uh
and into a more multi-role fighter
aircraft. But the effect is the same.
The We can still deliver bombs on target
with a multi-role aircraft like Typhoon.
And the difference is we don't need to
carry as many because we can precisely
put those bombs where we'd like to. And
in terms of that capability, how
flexible is it? Because in the old days
we'd have bomber pilots and we'd have
fighter pilots. Now, as a Typhoon pilot,
you have to do both. We have to do all
roles. Yeah. So our our two squadrons
our two frontline squadrons here at
Coningsby, the pilots are trained in all
roles.
And and we can swing from one to the
other almost on a daily basis. Now going
back say 70 years to those heady days
during the war when bomber command
possessed thousands of aircraft.
Is it possible to equate a squadron of
Typhoon say to a number of squadrons in
terms of the punch that they can pack?
You got to just go back to what the
effect is you want. So if you want to
take down let's say World War II a
number of factories, you would you would
calculate how many bombs you would need
to
to do that
and get actually on target.
Then you'd work back and say, "Well,
this would take 20 Lancasters." And with
the accuracy of those weapon aiming
systems and the bomb itself, that that's
probably how much you'd need.
With Typhoon we can say um
that bomb will go in that particular
place. We don't need as many aircraft to
do the same mission because the the
technology allows us to be more precise
in what we're delivering.
Now we do live in very different times.
The threats that are posed towards the
United Kingdom now come in varying
forms. Yes. How quickly can your boys
get airborne?
Um
how long's this piece of string? And we
like to keep people guessing. [laughter]
We like to seal the question. Yeah. I
mean every minute of every day we're
we're ready to to tackle whatever threat
is is put the UK's way and you know
we're here to defend our skies.
Justin, you've had
the chance to fly some of the most
iconic aircraft that the RAF have
possessed over the last 75 years,
starting with the Spitfire and now
currently on the Typhoon,
what's your favorite?
Uh it's a it's a difficult question. I
as you said, I've flown some some pretty
serious hardware. Um Typhoon is
uh the most awesome fighter jet that
I've flown.
Uh
the power it has is is truly remarkable.
However, the the Spitfire just has that
X-factor.
Uh it is it's iconic.
It carries with it uh a lot of history,
uh a lot of uh of memories, uh and it is
a a true fighter pilot's aircraft. So,
the the Spitfire has it. When you fly a
Spitfire,
your mind must cast itself back
to the days when that was developed uh
and to those men who flew it. I I had
one particular moment flying a Spitfire
over Kent where I realized I was flying
through the same airspace that the
Battle of Britain happened, you know, 75
years ago.
Uh and that was quite an emotional
moment when I you know, sat in a
Spitfire in that bit of airspace. So,
we're very proud of our history
and that ethos carries on today with the
fighter pilots across the runway here on
the front lines.
Coningsby is a survivor. It was
christened in the 1940s. It evolved
through the Second World War, the Cold
War, and today remains very much at the
front line of Britain's air defenses
here in the 21st century. It's aircraft
from the Battle of Britain Memorial
Flight with its Hurricane, Spitfires,
and of course its Lancaster through to
its modern squadrons of sophisticated
Typhoons in many respects encapsulate
the story of the RAF. But also, there's
something else. Not only does it capture
its spirit, it also points the way to
its future.
>> [music]
>> For over a century, the legendary tales
that have surrounded our great British
airfields have inspired
>> [music]
>> generations of people, including me.
Which is why I am on a personal mission
to cross the UK to visit some of our
most important airfields. To understand
[music]
not just about their contribution to our
past, but importantly, how many of them
have helped define our future.
From the UK's first flight [music]
through to groundbreaking innovation
such as carbon fiber and the jet engine,
and the extraordinary effort spent on
preserving our aviation heritage, join
me as I explore the story [music] of the
airfields that have helped shape Britain
and the world.
Today we are at Bournemouth Airport.
It's a small regional airport on
England's south coast and today it
caters for about a million passengers a
year, most of them heading out on
holiday. But 70 years ago, life here was
very different because back then, during
the Second World War, this was otherwise
known as RAF Hurn. And in those days,
the skies above me would have echoed to
the roar of hundreds of Allied aircraft.
During World War II, RAF Hurn was only
operational for 3 years, but its time as
a transporter and fighter airfield was
put to good use. It was home to a range
of aircraft, including gliders,
Mosquitoes, Wellingtons and Typhoons.
RAF Hurn was built because following the
invasion threat of the summer of 1940,
the air ministry thought it could occur
the following year, and a large number
of defensive airfields were built along
the south coast. Herne was one of them.
It was constructed during 1940 41,
and it was opened on the 1st of August,
1941. But, by that time, the threat of a
second invasion had passed. And so, it
was not needed [music]
for its initial purpose.
Herne was used for training by airborne
forces.
They were dropping paratroopers and also
training in towing gliders, which were
going to be used for D-Day.
Gliders were first used in combat by the
Germans.
These engineless aircraft allowed them
to glide silently to their targets
unnoticed,
dropping troops in precise areas and in
concentrated groups.
It wasn't long before [music] the UK and
her allies developed their own force.
The Glider Pilot Regiment was deemed
necessary following the German attack on
the Belgian fortress of Eben-Emael in
1940. Following the success of that
German offensive, Winston Churchill
decided that the ability to move men and
material ahead of the front line was
something that we should investigate and
build on.
In February 1942, the Glider Pilot
Regiment was ready for battle.
It was a cooperation between two forces.
The pilots would be recruited from the
British Army,
but they would be trained by the RAF.
The first major glider operation of the
Second World War was the assault on
Sicily in 1943.
The operations were a success. Um all
targets were achieved, but there were
heavy losses. About 50% of the gliders
used landed in the sea, and um a lot
were hit by anti-aircraft fire on the
way [music] in.
During World War II, there were three
main Allied gliders.
The Hadrian, made by the Americans,
could take 13 men and their equipment.
But, it was soon superseded by the
British Horsa, which was larger and
heavier.
The biggest glider was the Hamilcar,
which took [music] heavy loads,
including light tanks. One of the
problems during the Sicily landings,
when they were using the Hadrian gliders
is that if they wanted to deliver
[music] anti-tank artillery, the
anti-tank gun and the Jeep required to
pull it would be carried in two separate
gliders. If one of them didn't make the
landing zone or was was lost, then
obviously that meant the load was
unusable. Um therefore, in following
operations, they tried to ensure that
those loads were taken in a Horsa glider
where the Jeep and the anti-tank gun
could be carried together. Thus, you'd
have a fully working load as soon as the
glider touched down.
The Horsa was used by the Glider
Regiment in all its major operations.
The prototype first flew on the 12th of
September, 1941, and it was operational
until 1945.
It was maneuverable in flight and could
carry up to 25 troops.
Built mainly of plywood, it was 67 ft
long with a wingspan of 88 ft, and it
could glide at a speed of 100 mph.
During the Second World War, the Glider
Pilot Regiment took part in 14
operations. These varied in size, the
smallest involving two gliders, the
largest nearly [music] 700. Over the
course of the war, they lost nearly 600
men killed in action as well as many
more wounded and taken prisoner of war.
World War gliders were often referred to
Riley by their crews as flying coffins,
but to get a real idea of the challenges
their pilots faced, I've come here to
join the gang at the Buckminster Gliding
Club. They're based here at the former
RAF Saltby. From this runway, aircraft
and gliders [music] ferried lead
elements of the US 82nd Airborne
Division over to Normandy on the eve of
D-Day. This is a place steeped in
history, and with any luck, if the
weather clears up,
>> [music]
>> I might see it from the air.
Wartime gliders were towed most of the
way to their target by military
transport aircraft.
The one-way nature of the missions meant
they were viewed as disposable, which
meant they were made from common
>> [music]
>> and inexpensive materials such as wood.
Thankfully today, well, they're all made
from carbon fiber and built to last.
Well, that all seems to fit nicely.
Hello, Pete.
>> Hi, Jules. Nice to see you. And nice to
see you, mate.
>> Yeah.
Thank you for this.
You're all right, are you? No.
>> [laughter]
>> I hope you won't need it. Suits you,
sir. Now, I've never flown in a glider
before. What's it going to be like? Is
it going to be really quiet? Is it going
to be noisy, bumpy? Um I think today
will be fairly benign and upstairs
there'll be
uh very little turbulence, I would
think.
Um I can show you some turbulence when
we go through the the wake of the the
prop wash of the tug
just to replicate what would be
happening in wartime conditions flying
over the channel.
So, we can we can sort something out for
you. We'll get you sorted. Good. Well,
I'm ready to go. Come on.
Here we go.
Oh, quite bumpy.
And we're off the ground [music] now.
So, we're
following him.
Waiting for him to lift off.
Gosh. So, we're in the air. There he
goes.
Wow.
There we go. Tug's airborne. We're
airborne. Wow, that rush of air. You can
certainly hear it and feel it.
It's amazing.
Tug's just banking right now to the
right gently. Our tow line is nice and
tight. And there we go. Look, there's
Yeah.
Lincolnshire and Leicestershire in the
gloom. Yeah, we've just gone in the uh
low tow position. It's trying to
replicate what they actually did during
the Second World War. So, that would be
the position that they actually fly in.
It's easier to control the glider. Is
it? And of course, you've got the
aircraft in full view. It's a relatively
small aircraft, of course, uh that's
towing us. I imagine, Pete, that the
prop wash from a twin engine Dakota onto
a horse and must have been quite
destabilizing in some ways. Well, yeah,
I'll give you a little taste of that.
I'll just pull up into the prop wash of
the aircraft.
There you are. You can feel the prop
wash. Oh, we're starting to vibrate now.
>> Yeah, that's the vibration. Yeah. You
can imagine, as you said, twin engines,
four engines on Halifax's and
Stirling's. Yes. The air full of these,
hundreds of aircraft all
in close proximity as well. Even though
I've only been in the air for a few
minutes, getting a sense of what these
glider pilots had to do and the
conditions they operated in,
I think they have piqued my [music]
admiration, actually. They were often
flying at night. They had no power.
There was no second chance [music] once
the tow was cast off.
Being a glider pilot was one of [music]
the most dangerous jobs in the military.
During World War II, they suffered 50%
casualties
and won over 170 awards [music] for
valor.
During D-Day alone, 867
RAF and United [music] States Air Force
gliders flew to France with 100 pilots
becoming casualties.
And we should spare a thought, of
course, for the troops that the glider
pilots were ferrying. [music]
They didn't have the view I have, of
course, today. They were sat in the back
facing each other.
>> [music]
>> It was dark. They couldn't see where
they were going. They had to trust
implicitly the pilots that were taking
them into action. We're only up here
for, relatively speaking, a few minutes.
I wouldn't want to have to spend hours
contemplating the future flying all the
way over to occupied Europe, Pete. Yeah,
I mean, flying nowadays to us is second
nature. But some of these 20-year-olds,
18-year-olds, it's the first time they'd
had an aircraft. And no doubt they
suffered from real bouts of air
sickness. Yeah. You know, read stories
of them using the helmets as, you know,
to hold the vomit. So, the whole inside
of the glider would be a smelly place to
be, I would think.
I should think a large number of them
were terrified before they'd even got
out and met the enemy.
Now, Pete, you're going to demonstrate
for me quite a steep descent to
replicate the descent that the horses
would have taken during the war to get
themselves out of the danger zone as
quickly as possible and down on the
ground. The glider itself wanted to be
as little time in the air as possible
when it came off tow. Cuz that's when it
was really vulnerable to small arms
fire. So, what we'd have to do then is
to get down on the ground as quickly as
possible. Okay, well, um I guess we
should release that tow. Uh Jules
camera, Jules glider. Releasing in 5
1 Go. I'm releasing the tow now.
>> Yeah, go. That's it. Tow is gone. It's
gone. I'll sit steeply over.
Uh
target is flying right away.
To our right there, he's clear.
And now Pete [music] is flying us
independently. We're flying at 70 knots,
which is 10 knots under what the horse
would actually fly at. We'll increase
speed. We're going to be increasing
speed to 80 knots now. Okay. Which is
more a a replication of what the glider
was doing during the Second World War.
So, here's Saltby here. We're going to
come into it now. Stretching out that
main runway there that saw so much
action during the war.
70 men leaving here, heading over to
Europe. Many of them, of course,
sadly, would never come back.
But hopefully today Pete's going to
bring me safely down to land.
I suspect in a [music] very dramatic
fashion in a minute. We're going to get
into a normal chute situation
and then I'll immediately dump the
height Okay.
>> with the air brakes, okay? Here we go.
>> Okay. Going now down. Whoa!
Oh, yeah, that's it.
>> Brakes on.
Control [music] the descent, coming
down.
Wow, those brakes really are holding us
in the air. 180 knots there.
We're coming in.
And we're down. There we are.
Well, that was fantastic. And
thankfully, I didn't need my parachute.
And on arrival, no one's shooting at us.
The Second World War wasn't just about
fighting on land, at sea, and in the
air.
It was also about mental strategy, how
to mislead the enemy and promote
particular points of view. And what
better way to do it than by spreading
false information. In January 1943, 296
Squadron flying out of Hurn were tasked
with a much more subversive kind of
transport operation. Their mission was
to drop leaflets. Now, on the face of
it, that doesn't sound like a
war-winning operation, but that's why
I've come here to the lovely
surroundings of Beaulieu Abbey in
Hampshire to find out more.
Propaganda was spread through the
[music] occupied countries with the help
of Special Operations Executive known as
SOEs.
These were Churchill's secret army and
conducted undercover operations
including espionage, reconnaissance, and
sabotage.
Hello, Lee. Hi, Jules. Nice to meet you.
>> Nice to see you, too. Now, I do love a
country house, particularly one with a
story attached to it. What's Beaulieu's
tale? Well, Beaulieu was SOE's finishing
school. This is where SOE agents learned
their tradecraft. Now, leafleting
doesn't sound like a particularly
aggressive form of warfare. So, when did
it start and what was the idea? It
wasn't particularly aggressive, but it
was very much about breaking the morale
of your enemy.
Um it actually began on the very first
night of the war. Now, you've been
studying the leaflet war, the propaganda
war for many years, Lee. Presumably,
you've now seen everything that was ever
printed. Yeah, pretty much everything.
And um if you'd like to come this way,
I'll show you a few more examples.
Airborne leaflets have been used for
military propaganda purposes since the
early 1900s.
During World War II, the UK produced
around 2,500 different versions,
dropping a staggering 6 billion copies
behind enemy lines.
Now, who decided what would go into
these leaflets? Well, the the leaflets
were prepared by another secret
department called the Political Warfare
Executive. This department was staffed
with Foreign Office civil servants,
journalists, uh graphic artists, emigres
who had escaped from occupied Europe.
And they developed the leaflet themes,
very much playing on any Allied success.
Um
the theme was constantly hammered home
of the certainty of Allied victory, that
we were going to definitely win the war
eventually. And what would trigger a
leaflet drop? What would make them come
up with this? Um the the pace of the
war. So, for instance, um after the
victory at El Alamein in North Africa,
there was lots of leaflets and and
miniature uh pamphlets that dealt with
the victory. The German defeat at
Stalingrad uh was constantly hammered
home, as well as the Allied bombing of
Germany. Um when the thousand bomber
raids took place in Cologne, that was
constantly mentioned on leaflets. So,
what are we starting with here then,
Lee? For official use only. Well, this
is actually quite interesting. This is a
a piece of internal propaganda that PWE
produced for um
RAF aircrew to actually um encourage
them to to drop leaflets. RAF against
Goebbels. Exactly.
>> Brilliant. And do you think this booklet
did anything to persuade air crews that
what they were doing was worthwhile? I
think it it did help. Certainly
um air crews did
become interested in leaflet dropping.
Um in fact, most of the leaflets that
survived are not the ones that were
actually dropped, but the ones that were
kept as souvenirs by air crew.
And here we've got these two rather
plain-looking French women looking into
the window as Hitler. And I I wonder if
that's a kind of caricature of a very
rotund Göring.
>> It could well be. Making off with a
bottle of wine and a plateful of food.
In 1941,
Hitler announced a new European new
order,
um which would mean economic um
unity and a racially pure Europe.
And everyone was going to be prosperous
under Nazi rule.
>> Yeah, yeah. Well, this took a more
light-hearted view of what that actually
meant for the people of France. The
Germans are going to steal your dinner.
In studying the psychological and and
the propaganda war, you'll be well aware
of white propaganda
and black propaganda. For anybody not in
the know, what was the difference, Lee?
Well, what we've just been looking at is
a white propaganda. This is official
statements by the Allied government. So,
you know, everyone knew who this
propaganda was coming from. Uh black
propaganda, on the other hand, pretends
to be something it isn't. I have some
examples here to show you.
Where did you manage to track these
down? Some of it comes from veteran air
crew. Some actually comes from former
SOE agents and resistance fighters. And
this this little sticker was sent to the
French resistance in container drops.
And the sticker promises 6 weeks leave
for the entire U-boat crew. And it
follows um sabotage advice on how a
crewman could sabotage a U-boat. Sure.
>> That's incredible. Advice on how to
sabotage a U-boat?
>> Yes. And the advice was very simple. It
was um just turn a few valves in the
U-boat, and it would uh explode the the
ballast tank. That is absolutely
fascinating. You know, I have read many
accounts of U-boat crews towards the end
of the war sabotaging their boats
because the losses were so high.
I wonder if these little stickers did
have anything to do with it, if the two
things join up.
>> It's quite possible. Uh what would you
say this is?
Incredible to think these are all
original. That's fascinating. Um no
idea. All I can recognize is August
1941.
Looks pretty official. There's a stamp
on it.
Well, you say it's an original, it's
actually a fake.
But a genuine fake.
>> A genuine a wartime
>> wartime fake of um
German Russian coupons. But how would
faking a Russian book win the war?
Every time these were dropped, it puts
their system into chaos. They've got to
reprint new rationing documents. People
with these existing rationing documents
can't get their food or their clothes.
Um it just puts the whole system into
mayhem. And it was it was all about
making life in Germany more difficult.
>> [music]
>> The months leading up to June 1944 saw
the assembly and mobilization of the
largest invasion force in history.
[music]
It was around Herne, here on the south
coast of England, that hundreds of
thousands of men, vehicles, [music] and
all of their equipment were gathered and
trained. All in preparation for
Operation Overlord.
Overlord was the code name given to the
Allied invasion of France.
It involved nearly 3 million Allied
troops, 5,000 fighter aircraft, and
6,000 ships. [music]
The day it was launched was known as
D-Day.
Britain knew that to win the Second
World War, eventually she would have to
land
>> [music]
>> on Western Europe and try and defeat the
German army. Obviously, while Britain
stood alone, this was a a near
impossible task, but once the Americans
joined the war in December 1941 after
Pearl Harbor, American reinforcements
[music] started to come into Britain and
planning started to gather pace in 1942
and in 1943 in particular. And also
immediately before D-Day, the RAF and
[music] the US Air Force bombers were
strategically bombing large parts of
northern France, in particular targeting
transportation hubs such as the railway
network to try and prevent the Germans
[music] from bringing reinforcements to
the battle area quickly. So, air bases
like Heron started [music] to gear up
for D-Day several months before June
1944 ready for the [music] the final
push before the operation was launched.
Troops were assembled in ports [music]
roughly opposite their target beaches in
Normandy.
The American troops stationed in
Cornwall landing on Utah Beach, while
the British troops who landed on Sword
Beach [music]
were assembled in the Shoreham and
Portsmouth areas. The invasion fleets
were given very clear lines to sail down
across the channel to France.
The allies landed around 156,000 men
>> [music]
>> in Normandy on D-Day alone. That's just
in the first day, on five different
beaches. They were providing very close
support to the forces who were landing
on D-Day and later on during the Battle
of Normandy, they were providing
firepower to take on German units and
particularly vehicles and tanks, for
example, that were immediately in front
of them. And also, for example, the
Mosquitoes were slightly heavier bombers
than the Typhoons, [music] they were
more able to attack larger installations
such as fortifications.
Without the glider pilot regiment and
their targeted operations, the German
counter-attack could have been
catastrophic during the D-Day landings.
Well, 2nd of [music] June, I think it
was, we were
briefed for the operation. [music]
Well, up to that point we thought that
we would be supplying the French
Resistance, who are much in the news at
the time.
Uh but of course in the event when we
were briefed, it was for the big [music]
show, uh D-Day.
For us, the night before D-Day, and uh
our job was to take over the uh stores,
explosives, ammunition, and so on. The
operation initially should have started
uh on the night of the
4th of June, and we should have landed
in France on the 5th, [music]
but uh in the event, uh because of the
uh inclement weather in the channel, it
was pushed forward 24 hours.
Of course, when we were briefed, the
German army was on the run,
and there were just going to be a few
people [music] with pitchforks and so uh
to um greet us, but um
of course, it didn't turn out that way.
We were in uh very good heart, I would
say. We This was going to be a pushover.
The gliders had been tasked with a
critical mission.
Each glider carried troops and equipment
to attack and destroy a series of
strategically important bridges,
preventing the German army gaining more
ground.
I landed at the wrong place.
I'm quite glad I did, really, because
had I landed at the right place, there
were a couple of Germans there who were
taking prisoners and um shooting them in
the back of the head. From having landed
in the wrong place, we made our way to
the uh correct rendezvous, which was 8
miles inland. [music]
The equipment that I was delivering was
an ambulance jeep, and the trailer was
full of medical supplies, with bottles
of blood plasma, and that sort of
[music] thing. When they got to the
rendezvous at uh Tuteville, a Royal
Engineers officer commandeered the jeep,
so they turfed all the medical staff
out,
uh loaded the the trailer up with um
explosive, and um made their way down
through a town called Troarn to blow
this bridge. Of course I would say this,
but it was the principal bridge over
there on the Dives River. It's the one
through which the German armor would
have come
if they were going to mount any sort of
operation from the east. The mission was
a success and just 3 days after landing
in Normandy, Weeden returned to the UK.
Having successfully completed 10 vital
[music] operations throughout the war,
the glider pilot regiment was eventually
disbanded in 1957. It was a [music] very
good unit to be on.
Uh
that's how I think it should be
remembered.
Now once the Normandy beaches have been
secured, transport ships off the coast
started to unload thousands of men,
vehicles, field guns, but also huge
numbers of tanks. Now perhaps the most
famous is the American-built Sherman
which all the Allied armies used, but
British armored regiments had their own
homegrown favorite, a real monster, and
appropriately enough, they called it the
Churchill.
>> [music]
>> Nigel!
Good morning.
How are you? Very well. This is just a
joy to see. I've seen so many hulks of
these beautiful machines on training
ranges which have been used for target
practice, full of holes, shadows of
their former selves, but yours is in
pristine condition. It's like it's just
rolled off the Normandy beaches. Well,
it may well have rolled onto them, but
it stayed in service this tank until at
least the '60s. It was a bridge at the
end of an arc with a permanent bridge on
top.
>> So the turret had been removed.
>> Turret had been removed, but we know
from the records it was a Mark IV
6-pounder, so we've taken it back to
what it would have been. And this is in
fact one of the first tanks to leave the
production line. So, last out of
service, pretty much. First into
service, and the only one running in the
world. Now, during D-Day, these came
ashore in huge numbers. How effective
were they in suppressing the enemy?
Well, they they came ashore in in a
variety of guises, and one of the
amazing things about the Churchill was
that it became the backbone of what we
called the funnies.
So, they weren't just gun tanks like
this one. They were tanks that brought
bridges ashore, that brought rolls of
matting ashore, that would go across
shingle and up walls.
There were tanks that had flamethrowers,
and one of the adaptations of this tank,
which really helped, fired a huge thing
called a flying dustbin. It was a great
big explosive charge, went about 80
yards, and would knock out a pillbox, a
house, a fortification.
And between all of these specialized
vehicles, they helped to get the British
forces ashore, and then off the beaches,
and fighting inland. Cuz of course, what
you don't want in a beach landing is to
get stuck on the beach. But going back
to the Blitzkrieg of 1940, when German
armor rolled itself across Europe,
rolling up the Allied armies, one would
say right up to the case of Dunkirk,
those lessons of armor working with
close air support were not lost on the
Allies. And during D-Day, these tanks
again came into their own with a in
another kind of form, in another
adaptation of their use.
Talking to the aircraft. Yes, and the
the other thing to remember about
Churchill is it was an infantry tank,
and it's it's not a tank designed really
to take on enemy tanks. It was called an
infantry tank, it went slowly, it went
at the same speed as the infantry,
taking out targets that they couldn't,
and they in turn took out the guys with
the anti-tank bazooka-like weapons that
it couldn't deal with. And then above
you had the Typhoons, and the taxi rank
of aircraft coming in to help. It was a
fantastic combination of the different
arms, all coordinated by radio, which at
that stage was not in its infancy, but
really it was coming into its own. Now,
my grandfather served in one of these,
and I've never been in one. And it does
look roomy enough for two. I think you
should come up. It's It's a must. You
should drive it. Now, that is not for
I'm not going to refuse. I guess the
easiest way is probably
up at the front.
Here we go.
Well, I mean, to say it's roomy in tank
terms it's all relative, isn't it? But
it doesn't look a huge amount of room in
there. How many crewmen would be in the
turret there? Well, there are three.
There are two guys on this side,
commander and gunner, and then on the
other side, the person who loaded and he
had to operate the radio as well. 24
hours in this tank, nowhere to sleep,
you had to stand up all the time. It's
tough. The These guys went through a
lot. Now, how many of these still run?
This is the only surviving running
example of the Mark IV. So, the chance
to get behind the wheel, as it were,
today is a
>> I I think you must you must do it. Come
on,
let's get in there.
>> Driving a bus. Which hatch is the
driver's hatch?
>> It's on the right. This being a British
tank, it's right-hand drive.
>> Of Of course it is.
>> [laughter]
>> Yes, the one of the Americans didn't go
for them in a major way.
Just drop in. Drop in, put your foot on
the back of the driver's seat, on that
metal white metal strip. Yep.
And then just lower myself [music] in.
>> Yeah.
Gosh, it is roomier in here than a
Sherman. Much roomier.
>> Yes.
Oh, there we are. It's fascinating,
isn't it? Looking around me. This isn't
a place for the claustrophobic. No. But
an amazing field of view there. That
hatch is then closed. And if you look to
your right, there's one periscope.
>> This little tiny one here.
>> Yeah. That is tiny. That is really
>> your view of the world. That's why you
rely on the commander so much to tell
you left, right. You can't see past the
horns, the front of the tank.
And as you say that reliance on one
another, that unique bond amongst tank
crews, is still familiar in tank
regiments today, isn't it? It is, and I
I the only other group who would have
seen anything like it were the air crew
Yeah. who in many cases supported the
tanks. The the bond between the people
who totally [music] rely on each other.
Well, I've seen a lot of aircraft
cockpits.
This thankfully does look a little bit
simpler. It is. And the pedals are
exactly what you'd expect. On the left
is the clutch.
>> Yep. Middle is the brake and the right
hand bar is the accelerator.
>> Okay. Gear stick here? The gear stick is
there and and usefully [music] numbered.
And the important thing is the steering
and that's the two handles dropped down
in front [music] of you.
>> That's here. Yes.
>> Yep.
The thing to remember with this tank and
many of the tanks for this era and
beyond is that they'll steer in neutral.
So, when the engine's running, don't
move the steering handles unless you
mean to because the tank will slew. So,
basically, if you take your hands off
everything, it will just go forward in a
straight line. Indeed.
That's the theory. It is.
>> [laughter]
>> But first, we have to start it. So, how
do we fire it up, Nigel? Little switch
at the top of that panel. This one here,
turn it right? Okay.
And then the big button in the middle of
the instrument panel is the starter
button.
Wow. You can feel the whole tank moving.
What about the accelerator? Going to
give it a try, a bit of gas? Push the
throttle gently. It's quite stiff.
Oh, there it is.
That's quite a reassuring noise to go
into battle with, isn't it?
>> Yes, unless you're trying to hear each
other.
>> [laughter]
>> Let it ease the clutch up and steer
once. Let it start rolling, then steer.
>> Okay.
Here we go. We're cranking to the right.
Amazing.
Gosh, imagine going to war in one of
these.
It really is like sitting in the heart
of a dinosaur, this.
>> Yes.
There we are. And neutral. Neutral.
And turn the ignition off, I would
suggest.
Wow.
Nigel, thank you very much for that.
Short, but very sweet. And it's
fascinating to think that
when my grandfather was clattering
across France, high above him,
those Typhoons from Hurn were busy
taking out the enemy. Amazing. And so
important. You imagine how comforting it
must have been to know that you had air
support, because [music] the the enemy
that you were fighting you often
couldn't see. Yeah.
Yeah. And this wouldn't do at all. You
certainly needed some help from above.
[music]
Probably in more ways than one.
Absolutely.
>> [laughter]
>> By the end of D-Day, the Allies had
successfully landed on five key beaches
along the Normandy coast, but that
success had come at a high price with
some 10,000 casualties. And what's more,
the really vital job of joining up those
beachheads and securing key strategic
towns in the area was still ahead of
them.
At the end of August 1944, Paris was
finally liberated, effectively bringing
to an end Operation Overlord. At the
same time, huge numbers of Allied planes
were being moved from Britain to France,
and RAF Hurn's use as a military
airfield was coming to an end.
After the D-Day [music] landings, the
Typhoons across the channel operated
from Normandy. So, at that time, there
was no further military use for Hurn. In
August 1944, [music]
the Admiralty decided that Hurn would be
used as a civilian airfield for BOAC.
[music]
That was the national airline at the
time, British Overseas Airways
Corporation. Even though Hurn was now a
civilian airfield, [music]
it was nothing like an airport that we
know of today. There was no need for the
ordinary population even to think about
flying at that time. The war was still
looming over their head, and it would be
a long, long time before the British
public were able to use airline
services. [music]
The airport at Hurn became very
important because it was initially
Britain's only international airport.
Initial services from Hurn served Iberia
and North Africa, over to Cairo and out
to the Middle East. Then there were
plans to operate services to the
Commonwealth [music] again, and for this
purposes it was arranged to fly in
service with converted Lancaster bombers
from Hurn down to Sydney. Lancasters
[music]
were converted because at that time
there were no airliners available in
Britain. The bombers were converted, gun
turrets were removed, the bomb bays were
sealed up, and seats were put inside.
The flight to Sydney was advertised
[music]
as taking 67 hours, which meant stopping
three nights en route. The distance from
Hurn to Sydney was 13,400
miles, and the Lancastrians were able to
cope with this.
RAF Hurn had become Hurn Airport, but
due to its location over 100 miles from
London, it wasn't a hit with the
passengers.
So when London Heathrow [music] opened
in 1946, the airlines moved their
services to the new airport, leaving
Hurn with a different role.
The former Vickers Armstrong had a large
factory at Weybridge, and they also had
a large order book, which they couldn't
keep up with. So they were looking for a
second production site. Hurn was
selected, and they took over the former
BOAC hangars for production of Varsity
Trainers and Viscount Airliners. The
Viscount went on to be a worldwide sales
success, breaking into the magic North
American market. Production continued
until the final one was delivered at the
beginning of 1964.
The Vickers factory would continue to
produce successful airliners up until
1984. They even made parts for the
legendary Concorde. But when production
did end, well the airport had to
reinvent itself once again.
Aircraft may no longer be built [music]
here at Bournemouth, but much of that
earlier heritage does survive. Many of
the hangars that now surround the
airfield are full of companies providing
parts, maintenance, and essential
[music] services to the aircraft
industry.
Like this one.
Mike. Jules.
Pleased to meet you. Welcome to Jets at
Bournemouth. Thank you very much indeed.
This place is immaculate, isn't it? It
is. It's a corporate business aviation
center. We keep it clean because it
produces that type of work. And what
have you got in here? That looks
fascinating. That's a Dornier 328 prop
jet. Originally built in Germany, but
now um they've stopped making them, but
we have a approval to service them, and
this one is all the way up from Africa.
And what about this one, Mike? This is a
Hawker 800B, originally built in this
country, probably about 25 to 30 years
old. I have been astonished, traveling
around Britain's airfields, at how many
private jets there are. I always assumed
they were the preserve of the rich and
wealthy, just a handful of them in
Britain, but there are hundreds, if not
thousands. It may have started that way,
but there is a misconception about that
is the the rich and wealthy, but it's
not. It's now become a business tool,
and people are beginning to realize that
if you use them properly,
they can be very good and cost-effective
for your business. And the UK probably
has the second largest business aviation
community in Europe. Now, the boys look
hard at work here, Mike. What are they
actually doing to this aircraft today?
We are going to, because she's up for
sale now, and she's been on the ground
for a while, we need to put her on
sticks and exercise the undercarriage,
make certain everything is working, and
to check all the associated warning
systems with it in the flight deck. So,
if you'd like to join Bob up there, I'm
sure he can find something for you, too.
I would love to. I've never seen inside
a private jet. It's always been a kind
of secret world, but now's my chance.
Now's your chance, and please be my
guest.
Hey, Bob. Hi there, hi Jules. I'll get
to you in a minute, mate. I'm going to
quickly look in here. Look at this, the
world of the rich and famous, the
private jet. Now, Mike was saying this
aircraft is what, 25 [music] years old?
So, 1980s, it's certainly got that feel,
very kind of d- Dallas with all this
walnut and gold, but let's face it, it's
certainly better than flying economy,
isn't it?
Right then, come on.
Hello, mate.
>> [music]
>> How you doing? Look at this. Gosh, do
you know what? I was expecting this to
be very very tiny, but
it's about the same sort of size as a
jumbo, isn't it? It is. This aircraft,
although it's a lot smaller, requires
the same kind of navigation systems,
electronic systems that the bigger jets
So, what's Mike doing? Mike is just
going to turn the hydraulic rig on. That
will That will read 3,000 PSI.
>> just flickered into life. Yeah.
Just had a bit of a power surge there,
but what's happened there is the
hydraulic rig is switched on outside,
which is connected to the aircraft, and
that's giving 3,000 PSI Oh, just to the
hydraulic system there. Yeah, okay.
That's the brake pressure. Yeah. You are
now going to pull the undercarriage up
by operating that handle. Pull it to the
right and take it up. You'll see these
lights, those three green lights there
indicating that the landing gear is down
and locked, which is what the pilot's
looking for on his approach. Yeah. As
soon as you hit that handle, those
the red lights will come on, and that's
telling you the gear is traveling up,
and when it gets to up and locked and
it's all clean, Mhm. all those lights go
out. Right then, so
ready?
Okay, right, they're about to pull the
gear up.
Gear up.
Okay, you can go.
>> pull it to the right. Yep. And up.
Oh, it's quite a thump, isn't it?
>> It is. That's it That's it breaking
[music] the geometric locks. That's your
gear is up. up in there.
>> Yes.
That's the nose is up and locked.
Left hand main is locked.
Right hand main is locked. You're now
configured for flying. The gear is all
up All the doors are closed. The
aircraft is ready to fly.
Should we put it down then? You can put
it down. I'll just let the guys outside
know I'm going to do that. Gear coming
down. Gear down.
I just said you selected down.
That's the red cuz the gear is traveling
the moments It's down. Your nose is
locked down. Yeah.
Your right hand main is locked down.
Your left hand main is locked down.
Brilliant, Bob. Well, thank you very
much indeed. I have really enjoyed my,
albeit, brief glimpse
into the rather elaborate and
luxurious world of the private jet.
Before the world of private jets,
Bournemouth Airport's first civilian
flights were reserved for military VIPs
and wealthy individuals.
But, with the dropping costs of air
travel came the rise of the package
holiday. And one holiday company in
particular left its mark on Bournemouth
Airport.
Bath Travel was formed by my
grandfather, Reginald Ernest Bath, in
1924.
And he had a single travel agency in
Bournemouth. And in 1957, [music]
when R.E. Bath died, my father inherited
that one travel agency, which he grew in
the next 30-40 years into Britain's
[music] biggest privately owned travel
agency network.
The following year, my father decided
that it would be a good idea to have his
own flights. And so, he chartered a
plane to fly from Bournemouth to Palma.
But, in those days, it was incredibly
undeveloped. For example, there was only
one hotel on Magaluf beach called the
Atlantic.
Now, there's 35,000 hotel beds in Palma
Nova and Magaluf. So, Peter Bath
produced a very personal service. And in
1965, when we started the 1-11 jet
flights from Bournemouth, he would write
an individual letter to every passenger
on the plane, and it would be put on the
seats. And it was the
the lunch menu on the 1-11.
And he said, "Dear Mr. and Mrs. Shoot, I
hope you've enjoyed your holiday. And if
anything's gone even slightly wrong,
here's my number. Tell me about it." And
this was the kind of [music] personal
service which people loved. And the word
of mouth recommendation that he got from
dealing with every problem himself was
extraordinary.
As the tour operation grew, he started
adding more destinations.
April 21st, 1996, we flew a British
Airways Concorde subsonically from
Heathrow to Bournemouth with 100
passengers that we were taking up that
morning. We then put 100 passengers on
and flew the aircraft supersonically out
over the Atlantic for a champagne lunch.
But the big thing was, it was a lovely
sunny Sunday and at least 25,000 people
came out to the airport to see the
historic first flight of Concorde in and
out of Bournemouth. In the early days,
people went for a holiday for a week or
two weeks. By the time Ryanair and
EasyJet came along 15-20 years ago
flying daily services, people could go
on any day of the week and come back on
any other day of the week. So, for the
last 15 years of Palmair's life, we were
competing with low-cost carriers and we
had higher prices and people could only
go to Mallorca on [music] a Wednesday.
Whereas with Ryanair, they could go
every day of the week. At the end of
October 2010,
we operated the last ever Palmair flight
and it came back into Bournemouth and
the passengers were in tears, the
stewardesses were in floods of tears cuz
their job was finishing. But even the
day that we finished, technically, we
were still Britain's favorite charter
airline. In May 2009, we started Palmair
Express with a ex-British Airways Boeing
737-500.
Unfortunately, my father [music] died in
2006 in December.
So, we immortalized him by naming the
aircraft The Spirit of Peter Bath and my
mother initiated the naming ceremony at
the airport. We invited hundreds of
passengers to see the new aircraft being
unveiled. He will be remembered by at
least 150,000 local people who flew with
him often for 20 or 30 years as a person
who cared enough about his passengers
that he saw off every flight that he
possibly could. Without him, there would
be no Bournemouth Airport today.
What was RAF Hurn was created during the
conflict of the Second World War, but
unlike so many of its sister airfields,
it survived and played a crucial role in
the development of civil aviation. But I
wonder how many people taking off on
aircraft like that, heading away on
holiday to the Mediterranean and beyond,
really appreciate that they are flying
in the vapor trails of those Typhoons
that left here for Normandy over 70
years ago.
>> [music]